<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain and faithfull discovery of a beame in Master Edwards his eye. Or A moderate ansvver to the substance of the first and second part of Gangrena. Especially to his prophesie; wherein some of his stories are refuted; the manner of his comming by them questioned. His double dealing detected. Capt. Paul Hobson with some others, vindicated. Mr. Josiah Rycraft examined. Mr. Edwards unparalleld partiality, is impartially declared, and his prophesie truly reflected. / By Edward Drapes.</title>
            <author>Drapes, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E350_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201053</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861630</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861630</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81728)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E350[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain and faithfull discovery of a beame in Master Edwards his eye. Or A moderate ansvver to the substance of the first and second part of Gangrena. Especially to his prophesie; wherein some of his stories are refuted; the manner of his comming by them questioned. His double dealing detected. Capt. Paul Hobson with some others, vindicated. Mr. Josiah Rycraft examined. Mr. Edwards unparalleld partiality, is impartially declared, and his prophesie truly reflected. / By Edward Drapes.</title>
                  <author>Drapes, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed. And are to be sold by William Larner, at his shop, at the signe of the Blackmore in Bishops-gate-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Edwards, Thomas. Gangræna.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangræna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113769:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Plain AND FAITHFVLL DISCOVERY OF A BEAME In Maſter</hi> EDWARDS <hi>his Eye. OR A MODERATE ANSVVER to the ſubſtance of the firſt and ſecond part of</hi> Gangrena. <hi>Eſpecially to his Propheſie; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſome of his ſtories are refuted; The manner of his comming by them queſtioned. His double dealing detected. Capt.</hi> Paul Hobſon <hi>with ſome others, Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated. Mr.</hi> Joſiah Rycraft <hi>Examined. Mr.</hi> Edwards <hi>unparraleld partiallity is impartially declared, And his Propheſie truly reflected</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDWARD DRAPES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. 5.30, 31,</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A wonderfull and horrible thing is committed in the land.</p>
               <p>The Prophets propheſie falſely, and the Prieſts beare rule by their meanes, and my People love to have it ſo: And what will ye doe in the end thereof?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 7.3, 4, 5,</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And why beholdeſt thou the mote that is in thy brothers eye, but conſidereſt not the beam that is in thine own eye?</p>
               <p>Or how wilt thou ſay to thy brother, Let me pull out the mote out of thy eye, and behold, a beam is in thine own eye?</p>
               <p>Thou hipocrite, firſt caſt out the beam out of thine own eye: And then ſhalt thou ſee clearely to caſt out the mote out of thy brothers eye.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed. And are to be ſold by</hi> William Larner, at his ſhop, at the ſigne of the Blackmore in Biſhops-gate-ſtreete <hi>1646.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113769:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113769:2"/>
            <head>To the Impartiall Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AD not truth been more engaged in this following diſcourſe then my ſelfe, I ſhould have rejoyced in the continuing of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed ſilence. But ſeeing Maſter <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Goliah</hi> like, comming forth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Hoaſts of the living God, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſly aſſuming to ſtamp the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of truth upon thoſe many <hi>Apocryphall</hi> ſtories, faign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tales, and forged relations, contained in his <hi>Gangrena</hi> ſtrengthning the hands of the wicked, and ſadning the hearts of the Godly, and yet notwithſtanding crying out with great zeale <hi>the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord.</hi> For Sions ſake, I could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o longer hold my peace, but was conſtrained within me, to preſent this inſuing ſearch, of a <hi>Phariſaical</hi> ſpirit, and an infectious <hi>Gangrena,</hi> that is ſo much juſtified by her Children, to thy ſerious peruſall, and judicious conſideration; that if thy judgement hath been captivated, to give credit to it, it may at length be rectified. Or if thou art yet in doubt, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring like a wiſe man) to paſſe cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, before thou haſt heard what the accuſed can ſay for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mſevles I hope (through the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God) what I have written, will prove ſatisfactory to thee, and be a light to regulate thy judgement, by whoſe information (according to my own knowledge is my endevour which <hi>I</hi> have proſecuted, not with words to delight thy eare, but to profit thy inward man: I love to pleaſe no man beyond, and yet all ſo farre as may tend to their edification.</p>
            <p>Plain dealing without the leaſt flattery, is the true language
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113769:3"/>
of a faithfull friend, that is like the oyle, that doth not make, but heale wounds. The deriſion and reproaches of unreaſonable men, is my expectation: However I doubt not, but that truth which commands me to write, will ſecure me, and cauſe thee to accept it, though rejected by others, and me patiently to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe any thing for it, and learne me to bleſſe them that curſe me, and pray for them that diſpitefully uſe me.</p>
            <p>It was not my thoughts to anſwer all his ſtories, being a work imposſible for any one man, except he had the knowledge of the whole proceedings of every one of them, from the beginning to the ending of them, but rather to ſhew the untruth of thoſe ſtories I had knowledge of, and the ſtrange pharaſaical overſight of Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> his dwelling ſo much a broad, and ſo litle at home that ſo by ſome fruits, thou maieſt the better judge of the whole Tree.</p>
            <p>Some things M. <hi>Edwards</hi> chargeth Captain <hi>Hobſon</hi> with concerning his doctrine, which I have not particularly replyed to, becauſe I heare it will be abroad before long, to ſpeake for it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Reader, one thing <hi>I</hi> crave at thy hands, that thou wilt reade ſeriouſly, judge faithfully, not with a criticall eye, but with a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious heart, and reprove me, wherein <hi>I</hi> doe a miſſe charitably, ſo ſhalt thou truly engage him to thee, that loves thee in the truth, and the truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edward Drapes</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113769:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Plain and faithfull diſcovery of <hi>A BEAM IN Maſter</hi> Edwards his Eye.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is very remarkeable, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the woman was in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, the Serpent caſt out of his mouthwater, as a floud after the woman, that he might cauſe her to be carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the floud, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.14, 15. The condition of the Saints in this world, is moſt commonly very low: for while they are here, they are not at home, but wandring up and down ſeeking an honourable Country, dignifyed with immutable glory; but in the time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hi their voyage to that eternall <hi>Canaan,</hi> Sathan through his inveterate hatred, caſts out of his mouth flouds of water, viz. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling accuſations, oprobious ſcandals, horrid reproaches, and ſcorching perſecutions that (if poſſible) he may deſtroy them. For the end of all his motions, whether ſecret or more open, is, <hi>the Saints ruine;</hi> For the effecting of which <hi>Deſign,</hi> he hath many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, great <hi>Pollititians,</hi> inſtilling into them Leſſons full of blood, that when they ſeem moſt to ſmile, then is the greateſt miſchiefe by them intended, when <hi>Sathan</hi> transformes himſelfe into an Angell of Light, then is moſt danger; when he intended to deceive our firſt Parents, he told them that they ſhould be wiſe, even like unto God, when he perſwades men to kill the Saints, he tels them they ſhall doe God good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, he ſuits his actions to the Saints conditions; if they appeare to be but few, weake, or fearefull, he ſets upon them in the open field, withall his might and power, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them; if he findes them too ſtrong for him in the mountaines, he will aſſault them in the valleys; if open force prevaile not. he will take another courſe, he will diſguiſe himelfe; The <hi>Woolfe doth moſt harm when in ſheepes cloathing, Sathan</hi> hurts moſt, when he comes under the veile of piety, <hi>Learning and rich rewards</hi> to enſnare pore men; the Snake lyes hid oft-times in the graſſe, <hi>Sathan, Antichriſt,</hi> that man of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, oftenlye lurking many in Books, Pulpits, Sermons, Faſts, legall conformityes, and ſo are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onveyed into the hearts and ſpirits of men, like poyſon in a Cup of wine, ſince my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113769:4"/>
eyes was through the power of God, a little opened, I have diſcerned ſomething of the <hi>Myſtery of iniquity</hi> yet working, and that in many mens writings; but I can trul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay, I never ſaw more in any one, then in M. <hi>Edwards his Gangren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> both firſt and ſecond part, the Streames of which are ſurely <hi>Wormewood,</hi> all the waters thereof bitter, and the Fountain I feare Gall; The whole <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> foames forth big ſwelling words, and proud waves, threatning the ſuddaine and inevitable ruine of many Saints, veil'd with the name of <hi>Schiſmat qu s, Sectaryes, H retiques,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> (reproachfull tearms as old as <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o was the firſt author and inventer of them, and is the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuer of them againſt thoſe that have ſeen his nakednes, and departed from him)</p>
            <p>There are two things endeavoured to be effected by thoſe Book; The one, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all thoſe whom M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſtiles <hi>Independants, Anabaptiſts, Separatiſts,</hi> odious in the eyes of the Magiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate and People.</p>
            <p>The other, to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt himſelfe, and his <hi>Presbyterian Bretheren;</hi> in which he ſo inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ryes That this Deſign of his may be effected the ſtronger, and haſtened the ſooner, he propheſies the certain downfall, ruin, and deſtruction, of all thoſe, he calles, <hi>Independants, Anabaptiſts, Separatiſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> luſt like the Prophets that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to deter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>N h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miah,</hi> from the worke of the Lord in his hands, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 6.12, 13.14. Are not all the Letters in his <hi>Gangrenous Bookes.</hi> written by the Copy of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum's</hi> the Chancellour, and <hi>Sh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ribe, to the King to hinder the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Temple of the Lord, <hi>Ezzra</hi> 4.12. to the end of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6 verſe; ſaying, <hi>Be it known unto thee</hi> O Kings <hi>unto you</hi> O Parliament,, <hi>that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe People have been a rebell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous People, if you ſuffer them to incre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, or to l ve at peace amongſt you, they will be Kings themſelve, rebell, pay you no</hi> Toll <hi>nor</hi> Tribute, <hi>for they are a heady People, nemyes to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to Magiſtracy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore ſuppreſſe them, command them to deſiſt and to preach no more, leſt</hi> England <hi>be filled with their Doctrines, and wee loſe our</hi> Names, <hi>our</hi> Livings, <hi>our</hi> Tythes, <hi>and</hi> Offerings, <hi>and then what will become of us,</hi> for no man will buy our Merchandiſe <hi>any more, Rev,</hi> 18.11.</p>
            <p>I earneſtly deſire, that no man whom God hath called to worke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may be diſcouraged by this Propheſie, and that the Magiſtrates might not ſo liſten to thoſe ſtories, letters, and bloody accuſations, preferred againſt a generation of juſt men, as to command them to forbeare the building, repayring and adorning the Temple of God, with new and living Stones, built upon a ſure foundation, b lieving all things which their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies accuſe them of, ſo as to ſlight, diſregard, diſcountenance, and deſtroy them as enemyes, who have hitherto approved themſelves, in all their Straits, their cloſeſt friends; But that they, and all people, would ſeriouſly weigh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from whence this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie came, whether from a viſion or divine revelation, or whether the ground of it is not <hi>An I would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo, I deſire it may be ſo, and long till it is ſo, I ſhall never be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented til then, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſtand in my light, and keepe the Sunne of preferment from ſhining on me.</hi> As for the eight Symptoms layd own by him, and applyed to thoſe that in his dialect are <hi>Independ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts, Anabaptiſts, Sectaryes, &amp;c.</hi> They are to me the cleareſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his, and his Bretherens nakednes, that can be, and were they impartially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected, they would conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe it, and if they are infallible ſignes of ruin, they would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their own at hand; I ſhall briefly rehearſe the ſubſtance of them all in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as they are ſet down, and faithfully reflect them, that M. <hi>Edwards</hi> and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren may ſee, and be aſhamed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Symptom (as M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſaith, of the Independants ruine) <hi>is their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113769:4"/>
horrible pride, inſolency, and arrogancy, extolling themſelves to the heavens, deſpiſing all others, trampling upon them, yea, upon Kings, and Parliaments, the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>Aſſembly of Divines, and the Common Councell of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he City of London, which p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of theirs appeares in their writing, Speeches, geſtures and actions, in endeavouring to breake all, that will not da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce after thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe;</hi> from which he conclude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this, their Prid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> having gone before, their deſtruction will follow ſuddenly after. Here is a high accuſation, foule crimes layd to the charge of all thoſe whom he ſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Independants,</hi> had he as truly proved them as boldly affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med them, I had never dared to have app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ared for them, neither do I ſeeke the vindication of any mans pride or arrogancie, though he may be va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed with the name of an <hi>Independant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But that M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould charge the crimes of one or two, upon all that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Independants,</hi> ſeemes to me to be both uncharitable and unr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſonable: did I not k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow that envy makes wiſe men to forget themſelves, to doe they kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not what, and runne they know not whether, from one extream into another: I ſhould ſcarcely have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nduced to believe, that M. <hi>Edwards</hi> had forgotten the old rule, <hi>ex particulari non eſt concludendum,</hi> as I now ſee and know he hath if himſelfe knoweth what his Pen hath written. If one be proud, inſolent and arrogant, muſt all be ſo too? If one be a Heretique muſt all be Heretiques? If <hi>Iudas</hi> one of the twelve, veil'd with the name of a Diſciple, be a Devill, muſt all the eleven be Devils too? I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one Profeſſor be a <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> a <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mas Hymeneus</hi> or <hi>Philetus,</hi> muſt all the Profeſſors of Chriſt be ſuch? If one that is ſtiled by M <hi>Edwards</hi> or himſele, to be an <hi>Independant, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, or the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke?</hi> ſhould be in the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll of bitterneſſe, muſt all be ſo too, that go under that name? I deſire M <hi>Edwards</hi> would tell me what conſequence this is, whether it be good reaſoning, whether the grounds of it flowes from Religion or reaſon, from a plain demonſtration, or from a reaſonable ſuppoſition: ſurely all theſe reject and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre it as ſpurious, contradicting the lawes of God and man. I am very confident if one ſhould ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ape off the filth, ſoil, and dirt, that is to be found amidſt the refuſe of their Congregations, and throw it in his own face<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the face of the reſt of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren that abhorrs their Egyptian darknes; he would be very angry, cry out of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he ſhall hereafter ſay, he accuſed not all but ſome: then ſurely he hath dealt very maliciouſly and hipocritically, to make the world believe one thing in his Books, and himelfe to intend another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Is not this equivocation? &amp; Mentall reſervation? But if he ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k to his principles, to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emn all he had done well to have named more, for as yet he hath named but few, and ſome of them are never the worſe, for being named b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, their holyneſſe, integrity and honeſty, ſtanding ſtill unſhaken and unmoveable; ſome of them being ſo farre from pride, arrogancy, and ſeeking his or hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bretherens ruine, deſolation and deſtruction, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t I know would rejoyce to become his and their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rvants in the Lord Chriſt, <hi>though not in Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had but M. <hi>Edwards</hi> taken ſuch a ſtrict ſurvey, and made ſuch a through inquiſition into the Parochiall aſſemblyes, yea, into the very Angels and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em as it ſeemes <hi>by h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Epiſtle to his G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngrena</hi> he hath done into the <hi>INDEPENDENTS &amp; their Aſſembl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> he would have found a taske hard enough, an inco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nter ſharpe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have rooted out the pride, arrogancy, and inſolency that is between the Presbyterian Church walles, before he had ſo deſperately adventured to charge the guiltleſſ in the open field, had he lookt well before he had leapt he had ſaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe much labour; my ſoule deſires his inſtruction, not his deſtruction; Therefore I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113769:5"/>
deſire he would ſit down a little while, and conſider, what the Words of our Saviour meaneth, and faithfully apply the ſame, <hi>Math</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.2, 3, 4, 5. and ſee whether there is not ſpirituall abominations ſet up in high places amongſt them? Whether there is not darknes that may be felt amongſt them? Whether a ſpirit of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Prelacy,</hi> rules not even in them, who love the name, (oh that they had the nature) of Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines; Who extols themſelves more then the <hi>Presbyterians?</hi> Who makes ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oaſt of their wit, wiſdome, pyety, learning, reading, writing, reaſoning, as they, eſteeming all Ideots, Dunces and Fooles but themſelves, as if, with, and in them, and not in Ieſus, was the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge centred.</p>
            <p>If this be not true, let ſome man (if he can) tell me what the meaning is, of their <hi>ſtrange Petitions, invective Sermons, rancorus Diſcourſes, mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiſes, bitter threats,</hi> and endeavours to ſilence the mouthes of Lay men (as they term them) from declaring the ſweet injoyments of the tranſcendant excellencies of their beloved, of their God, of their King and of their Ieſus, communicated to them, rayling againſt them, with reviling, villifying ſpeeches, calling them diſgracefully <hi>illiterate, mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke, Taylors, Pedlers, Tinkers Coblers, and the like,</hi> carnally ſuppoſing (ſo far as I am able to ſpell their meaning) the gifts of the ſpirit to be centred in, and confined to the members of an <hi>Vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verſity,</hi> to humane learning, naturall education, acquired parts, &amp; the like, forgetting that it is the uſuall method of God, to invite the ſimple into Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Palaces, and to cauſe the weake and deſpiſed things of this world, to confound the wiſe, even ſhutting it out of their thoughts, or at leaſt out of their mouthes, <hi>that God hath choſen the weake things of the world to confound the things which are mighty, and baſe things of the world, and things wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch are d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpiſed, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are: that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence;</hi> 1. Cor. 1.25, 26, 27, 28 29. Surely did they conſider it, they would not ſo glory in the fleſh as they do, in their parts, learning, &amp; abilities, but rather in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Who can ſee their ſpirits, and not ſee arrogancy in its heigth? Who endeavours, plots, &amp; ſtudies, to be reverenced of all, to have the chiefe place at Feaſts, the higheſt place in their Churches, and to be called <hi>Rabbies, Doctors, Divines,</hi> like unto them? If a ſpirit of pride may be ſeen, in endeavouring to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing all People, high and low, rich and pore, Rulers and ruled, under the yokes of their own opinions, in pain of <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Maranatha,</hi> ſavours of Pride, how will they free themſelves from ſuch a ſpirit? If they imagine they can, let them tell me what they mean by preſcribing Lawes, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Cenſures, for them, over whom Chriſt hath given them no power? What do they intend by their pronouncing judgement and vengeance upon thoſe that diſſent from them? By their exclaiming upon the Parliament, for not heati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g a furnace ſeven times with hot ſcorching perſecution, to deſtroy many of Chriſts tender L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbes? For not being their executioners? If to incenſe a Parliament againſt an honeſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their <hi>tryed Servants,</hi> if to be jealous of, ſpeake againſt, and cunningly inſinuate a diſaffection in many againſt a Parliament, and the faithfull inſtruments of Englands preſent deliverance. If to ſit down in the throne of Chriſt, if to take his Scepter out out of his hands, his Crown off his head: If to deſpiſe, trample upon, and abaſe his membe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſavours of pride and arroggancy, (and pride and arrogancy is a certaine ſymptom of preſent diſtinction) as M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſayth, Oh then what a condition are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erians</hi> in! But I paſſe to his ſecond Symptome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Symp ome of the Sectaryes <hi>ruin and deſtruction,</hi> (for ſo he feares
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113769:5"/>
not to call the wor ſhippers of the living <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od) <hi>is their v olent preſecution of their wayes and cauſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What he may meane by their wayes and cauſes, it is very ambiguous. If by wayes and cauſes, he mean their conſtant endeavours of ſubduing the Kingdoms Enemies, (In which Cauſe he makes the world believe ſo many of them are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted,) then I confeſſe they have made haſte, <hi>though not more haſte then good ſpeed,</hi> &amp; through the power of God, have done that in a few Monthes, which others have not done in yeares: Now if their violence in promoting the Kingdomes peace, in purchaſing the liberty of free born Subjects, in haſting an end to the warres, and heavy taxes, that for the preſent are neceſſarily impoſed upon the Kingdome, be the violence he meanes, which portends their deſtruction; then am I verily perſwaded, there is ſome cunning underhand plotting, contriving, and conſpiring, their ſpeedy ruin, which himſelfe is an agent or factor in, which he aſſumes to himſelfe as the ground of his Propheſy. But is there no remedy but they muſt dye, who, under God, have been the inſtruments, that he and his bretheren live? Pore ſouldiers! that have adventured their lives, leſt their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, hazarded their utter ruin for them, even to the expence of much treaſure and the loſſe of much precious bloud; when they might juſtly expect to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and entertained in great triumph, M. <hi>Edwards</hi> himſelfe ſinging before them, and bleſſing God for them, they can hope for little elſe, then a bloudy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of all their labours.</p>
            <p>Or if he mean their Cauſe to be, their contending for the ſpeedy ſolemnization of a happy marriage between Truth and Peace, that theſe Kingdomes may be bleſſed in their ſweet embraceings each of other, &amp; their praying for it, their preach ng, writing, and contending for it, by no other Sword, then that of the Spirit, to be their violence; I acknowledge ſuch a cauſe, and ſuch a violence, I am willing to own, who ever condemnes me for it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>But if he meane by their wayes, <hi>error, Hereſie, ſchiſme,</hi> as it is probable, and by their violence, their conſtant endeavours to proſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te their errors, &amp;c. <hi>I</hi> will not deny, but ſome may ſtand up for errour, in ſtead of truth, but that he ſhould charge all thus, is unreaſonable; I wiſh he would deale ingeniouſly, and tell me, whether he believeth they know thoſe things to be error, hereſie, and ſchiſme which they proſecute, or not; if they doe not, will nothing expiate a crime of ignorance, but by the abſolute ruine of the offender? If it be ſo, who could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main alive? If the <hi>Independants</hi> are guilty of their thouſand errors, ſure I am the <hi>Preſbyters</hi> are guilty of their ten thouſands; and for the manner of he proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of theſe wayes, if the <hi>Independants</hi> uſe <hi>Wh ps,</hi> I am ſure the <hi>Pr ſbyterians</hi> uſe <hi>Scorpions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I could tell the world of many wayes and deſignes of heirs, of their great huge, vaſt endeavours to ſet themſelves on high; I could tell how l ke <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> they ſeeke preheminence above their Bretheren; I could alſ decla e how violently they carry on this their Deſign, like <hi>Iehu they d v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f rio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly,</hi> wi h a ſeeming ſhew of great zeal, trampling upon all that ſtand in their wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their teeth, to thinke a pore <hi>Mordecai</hi> will not bowe to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> m, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to hang him on a Gall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wes fifty Cubits high O the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of theſe men! O the uncharitablne! O the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d heartednes! O the cruelty f theſe men! How many Sermons have they preached? How many Papers ha they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113769:6"/>
preſented? How many Petitions, Epiſtles have they written and preferred, to the Parliament, ſtufft full with accuſation, againſt a company of pore men, that ſtand in their light; deſiring the Parliament may be the executioners, to cut the <hi>Independants</hi> off, in the mean while, I challenge all the world to name any <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants</hi> that have preferred one Petition to the Parliament, for th r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in of the <hi>Preſbyterians:</hi> Have they not rather ſate ſtill, and in all their Petitions deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ruled by the Parliament in all civill things, then <hi>to rule ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r them, at the other have done?</hi> How violent is M <hi>Edwards</hi> and his Bretheren againſt all thoſe that ſubmit not to <hi>uniformity, which few knowes,</hi> (ſcarce themſelves, that a e the greateſt ſticklers for it) <hi>what it is, and none knowes what it may be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> If to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſire the Timber that is in the houſes of thoſe that wake not as they do, may be pul'd down, that Gallows may be made of it, at their own d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng them on; if to ſay, they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te the <hi>Independants</hi> as Toads, yea with a deadly hatred, and the l k, ſav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs of violence? Two great Champions of the rs, Mr. <hi>Byfield</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> to name no more, will evidently prove their violence to be of a <hi>ſcarlet die,</hi> and if violence preſage ruin to the violent, let M <hi>Edwards</hi> and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth ten looke about them. <hi>Violence was the practize and the ruin of their Fathers the B ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Fathers have eaten ſowre Grapes, it is no wonder if the childrens teeth beſet on edge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come to the third Symptome, which M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſayth; is, <hi>the Independants great proſperity, ſtrange ſucceſſe in their wayes, and opinions, every wind fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring them</hi> If by their proſperity in their way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, he meanes the great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes God hath given them, in manageing any truſt repoſed in them? I am ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he ſhould ſo farre maligne the Kingdomes happin ſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if he meanes their proſperity in their wayes, to be their encreaſe in number? M e think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he ſhould not thinke that ſtrange ſucceſſe, ſince in another place he ſayth, they are bu an it conſiderable Party. If he intends by their ſucceſſe, the <hi>toleration of them in this Kingdom,</hi> let him conſider, whether he &amp; his bretheren are not tollerated al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, was there ever any Ordinance paſſed for the eſtabliſhment of <hi>Independency,</hi> is there hath been for <hi>Presbytery,</hi> their number is greater, a nationall Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them, every Pariſh Church is frequented by them; who are eſteemed like them? the Church Dores, the Pulpit dores are open for them, 200 <abbr>l.</abbr> or 300 <abbr>l.</abbr> or 400 <abbr>l.</abbr> and more, <hi>per annum</hi> attends them, large benefices, g e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtore; what (if they were contented) could they deſire, that they have not?) Will nothing ſatisfy them till they have <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, untill they have taken away the <hi>Independants</hi> Inheritances from them? It ſeemes all their ſucceſſes are nothing, ſo long as <hi>Mordecay</hi> doth not homage to them.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith <hi>Scotland hath been afflicted with Sword and peſtilence,</hi> If ſo, I deſire M <hi>Edwards</hi> would ceaſe to judge of perſons and thing, by common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, for his own words confeſſe his bretheren, the Presbyterians, even the <hi>Scots</hi> themſelves, may be ſubject to the Peſtilence; and would not wonder that two of M <hi>Goodwins</hi> children dyed of the plague; thus, if ſucceſſ s and proſperity fore tell ruin, it is high time for him and his bretheren to repent, for they ſit as Queens, &amp; the world wonders after them; But I come to the fourth Symptome of ruin</p>
            <p>Which M. <hi>Edwards ſaith, is the great plotting of the Sectaryes,</hi> (forſomuſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113769:6"/>
all Independants in Mr. EDWARDS Dialect be called, though let me tell him, it had been much better for him ſolidly to have (if he could) firſt proved them ſo, and not ſo unadviſedly to have cryed out, VENI, VIDI<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> VICI, but this is a cunning plot, whoſe foundation is layd in the bottomleſſe Pit, to render many Saints odious) He tels us in the generall of plotting, but what thoſe plots are, he knowes not how to deſcribe: like ſome of his bretheren, that in the frontiſpiece of their Bookes, write a confutation of divers errors, and in the body of their diſcourſe, ſcarce lay open what the errors are, they would (if they could) confute. But if he meanes the Independants riſing up early, ſitting up late, riding, running, fighting, ſtudying, by all honeſt wayes, juſt endeavours, to make theſ Kingdoms exceed their former beauty, in the injoyment of Peace and pyety, this is a matter of thanks and joy, not of murmring, repining, and ſorrow; Oh that he would ceaſe to blame that generation of men, upon whoſe reputation he cannot faſten one ſtain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It remaines for him; or any elſe, when they can, to prove that ever any of thoſe that are ſtiled Independants, were guilty of one plot againſt this Kingdom, or that they ever falſified any truſt repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them; if be or any of his brethren can ſhew it, let them bring forth their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, let them declare the time when the Plot was, the place where, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how: and when they haue proved them guilty, I believe none will refuſe to ſuffer; &amp; till then, let them ceaſe to make the world believe ſo. But if plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, contriving, Machiavilian, Jeſuiticall courſes and wayes prognoſticates de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, I ſhould rejoyce if they could exempt themſelves from it. If they ſay they can, I demand of them, what meanes their <hi>Syon Colledge Plots, their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed Petitions and Papers, their Remonſtrances, their ſubtill inſinuations into Magiſtrates, and People, againſt the Independants,</hi> poſſ ſſing them that they are an heriticall, ſchiſmaticall People, a People enemies to government, to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that would live under no Lawes, crying out crucify them, crucify them, away with them, away with them, they are unfit to live. D d Machiavill ever more cunningly ſeeke to intrap and deſtroy his oppoſers, then M <hi>Edwards</hi> as his <hi>Gangreous Epiſtle</hi> teſtifyes, by his Going, Writing, Eaves dropping, his ſending his Spyes, Emiſaries, Agents and factors abroad, to pry into the halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, failings, infirmityes, and nakednes of his bretheren, and having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered any, expoſing them to a publique ſale, to the view of all men, even to his own ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me. Thus may M. <hi>Edwards</hi> if his eyes be opened, ſee his own Picture, lively delineated by his own Pen, even to be ſuch a Picture, that I thinke will not e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſily be found among them he intended it for.</p>
            <p>But I proceed to examine his fift Symptome of the ruine of thoſe he calles In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Annabaptiſts, &amp;c. Whih he ſaith is this, <hi>that Independency is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> which he aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes to prove thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is not carried on in Gods way, as a matter of Religion, but with policy, tricks and the like.</hi> If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o plead Chriſt, the Apoſtles, and the Scriptures for their practiſe, be to manage it with tricks; he ſayes true, elſe how he will vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the truth of that which he hath ſaid, as yet appeares not unto m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he and his bretheren would look at home, and conſider what way of God it is for poor decevable men, to make <hi>Canons, Lawes &amp; Ordinances,</hi> as Iron bonds, to bind the conſciences of thoſe that differ from there in, what is their Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113769:7"/>
by Biſhops, is that the way of God? They will tell us their Ordination is good, becauſe they received it not from the Biſhops as Biſhops, but as Presbyters, who ſhifts now? What mental reſervation, evaſion, and equivocation is this? Is not this a trick of tricks? The Ordination by the <hi>Pope,</hi> by the ſame argument may be pleaded for, <hi>he is a Presbyter too.</hi> What is their maintenance by Tythes, Oblations, and Obventions, forced from all ſorts of men, the way of God? Is this <hi>Jure divino?</hi> If they ſay ſo, I deſire they would prove it; if they plead <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re humano,</hi> as that ſeemes to be their ſtrongeſt ſtaffe, then it is but mans way. What ſay they to their <hi>Parochiall, Claſſicall, Provinciall, and Nationall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> be thoſe <hi>Jure divino?</hi> Is thus to manage their presbytery mans way, or Gods way? Surely theſe are not the waies of God, but of man, like <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzas</hi> lovely Image, excellent for brightneſſe, terible for forme, whoſe head is gold, whoſe breſt and armes Silver, his belly and thighs of braſſe, his legs of Iron, his feet, part of Iron, and part of clay, is not their government a meere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, of gold, ſilver, braſſe, Iron and clay? But ſee the event of the Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35, 39. <hi>When will the Aſſembly anſwer the Queſtions propounded by the Parliament? I feare ſome tricks, and ſhifts now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith <hi>many that know not what Independency is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are ſticklers for it, and would not be tyed to it.</hi> Oh when will he ſee the beame in Presbyteries eye? Let him but reflect, look back, and ſeriouſly ask his owne ſoule the queſtion, whether Presbytery is not guilty, and that in a higher degree, of that which he chargeth Independency? Let him look into his large Church, I meane the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, the Mother, or into the Parochiall, her Daughters, and ſee whether he will not find ignorance, darkneſſe, groſſe ignorance, darkneſſe that may be felt, among many of their aſſemblies; doe they all know what Presbytery is? (if they doe, I think they know more then their teachers) how often have many of them compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ined of the ignorance of their pariſhioners? But to diſhonour the Independents, they are made Saints, wiſe men in a moment; how many amongſt them have their Religion yet to chooſe, waiting for the knowledge of what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion the Aſſembly hath, or wil ſet up. Which when they ſhall do if they adheare to their principles, and excommunicate all the profane, and groſſe ignorant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, they will fill the Kingdome with combuſtion, and people will ſhortly as ill indure their <hi>Tyranicall Judic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tures and ſenſures,</hi> as they did the <hi>High Commiſſion and Sar-chamber of late.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He affirmeth Independency to be a faction, <hi>in that all other errors and Sectaries are ſuffered, pleaded for, dealt gently with, are freely ſuffered to grow &amp; increaſe, no way taken to ſuppreſſe them, their Books. Licenſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I am ſorry to ſee ſo much envy, hatred &amp; mallice, appeare againſt the Parliament, as doth in this and many other paſſages, of the <hi>Gangrena,</hi> and all becauſe they cannot fulfill a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant humour, that is ſo much predominate in his Spirit, even to the diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe whoſe converſations, parts, piety, and ſound judgments, are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to any. He that runs may read envy in his ſpirit, how angry is he that any are Licenſed to ſpeaketh their owne defence, to wipe of that dirt, he hath indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to beſmear their faces withall (a priviledge that Heathens allow) as the Prieſts would not let the Scriptures be in Engliſh, leſt the people ſh uld underſtand their wickedneſſe, ſo many <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> now are extreame unwilling that the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113769:7"/>
preſſe ſhould be open for all, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t their folly ſhould be laid open, and their mouths ſtopped, and ſo not only their craft ſhould be in danger to be ſet at nought, but alſo that their <hi>Temple of the great goddeſſe Diana,</hi> ſhould be d ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſed, and her magnifence be diſtroyed, whom the world wonders after, and worſhips.</p>
            <p>If M. <hi>Edwards</hi> or his brethren could once monopolize Printing and Licenſing into their owne hands, that nothing might be Licenſed, nor Printed, but that which may tend to the advancement of their pompe; then might all thoſe tales and ſtories, lyes and libells, forgeries, quaint fictions, and bold malitious inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of which the <hi>Gangrena</hi> is compounded, paſſe for currant coyne in the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> judgment, and that by the Authority of <hi>Imprimatur James Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi> will they never be contented that others ſhould have the ſame priviledge as they themſelves have? Are not the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſuffered? <hi>Eraſtians, Ridged Presbyterians and the like?</hi> When will they be contented to obey and be Subjects will nothing content them but Rule, Dominion and Lord ſhip? Had the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall</hi> nature as well as name been ſuppreſſed, wee had not had this day any ſuch ſpirit in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="4">4 He ſaith that it appeares to be a faction, <hi>in that theſe ſorts of men come into it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Needy and broken men.</hi> 2. <hi>Guilty and ſuſpitious men.</hi> 3. <hi>Some who have buſineſſe depending, that they may be ſooner diſpatched.</hi> 4. <hi>Ambitious, proud, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous men.</hi> 5. <hi>Libertines, looſe perſons.</hi> 6. <hi>All wanton, wicked, unſtable Heretiques and</hi> 7. <hi>Such as would not have peace; looſe Offi es &amp;c.</hi> 8. <hi>And Many diſcontented in their Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the confluence of all theſe will prove Independency a faction, much more will it prove Presbyterie one, for firſt it appeares, their Church is compounded of ſuch, and that by his owne words, that ſay they come from them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All theſe ſorts of perſons are yet with them; how many men broken and needy are with them? and it may be honeſt men too for all that. How many guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amongſt them, witneſſe. <hi>Hunſcot</hi> and others. Is there none in their third place, that hath buſineſſe depending, who are with them? Even thoſe that one while was for <hi>Prelaticall,</hi> are they not now for <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> government? Surely they they cannot yet forget, who had, and hath a fine deſigne, that went from <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> to them, 4. <hi>I</hi> have already ſhewed there are ambitious proud men amongſt them; and who more covetous then they? Doe they not make it an ordinary thing to forſake one, a ſecond, yea a third, leaving two for a greater? Doe they not preach for lucre ſake? what ſavour hath ten ſhillings, twenty ſhillings, for a Wedding, Chriſtning, Funerall Sermon? ſurely covetouſneſſe in a high degree. Have they not heard of the great <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſter, at <hi>Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hmond</hi> that when a dead corps was buried in his pariſh, becauſe the man that had formerly relation to it, gave the Clerk but five ſhillings, the Miniſter ſaid it ſhould be taken up againe, and ſo accordingly it was; if Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> can paralell this amongſt all his ſtories of the Independents, them let him brand them with abominable covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Is their no Libertines amongſt them? and,</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whereas he ſaith <hi>all wanton witted perſons, come to the Independents. I</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire his pen may not here after, ſo haſtily out run the truth: Have they not one wanton witted man, unſtable man amongſt them? If ſo why doe any come from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113769:8"/>
them, but contradictions in his diſcourſe is ſo common, that he ſcarce thinks of them. Is there n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> looſe perſons, no libertines among them, not one heretique, that is ſtrange? But ſurely if lacivious, effeminate, ſcurrilous paſſages, carriages, deportments, and expreſſions, will manifeſt they have; <hi>I</hi> am confident hundreds of inſtances would ſoone be produced for the proofe of it, and not one of them of the Independents.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This he ſaith, <hi>Such as have no mind to peace, and are affraid to looſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and places, come to the Independents.</hi> This charge is bitter; doth, he not inſinuate into the Kingdome, that the Independents, in the Army, doe inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prorogue the warre, being afraid to looſe their places; Whether this be true or no, let their worke, haſt, ſucceſſe, endevours, winter and ſummer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, all crowned from Heaven with unparaleld ſucceſſe, ſpeake; there is a cloud of witneſſes; I will hold my peace.</p>
            <p>But that theſe ſorts of perſons are among them, let the former delayes of the Armie, witneſſe, that cruell and inveterate Spirit, among Miniſters, Officers, and people, at the reduced Army, that God hath made famous by not doing their work negligently, calling them the new Noddle, greene headed boyes and the like; if they be not enemies to peace, why are they ſo violent for the Magiſtrate to ſheath his ſword in the blood of the Independents?</p>
            <p n="8">8. He ſaith <hi>the Independents are diſcontented perſons;</hi> but are they ſo? I pray at what? it is becauſe they find nothing among or in their Churches fit ſubjects, or objects for divine contentments, but certainly there is few others among them, from the taleſt Cedar in the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> to the loweſt ſh ub in their pariſh-churches: I will declare what they are diſcontented at very briefly, that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> if poſſible, might ſee by his owne candle,</p>
            <p n="1">1 At God, that fire comes not downe from Heaven, to diſtroy a generation of men that deſerve better things at their hands, like <hi>Jonah,</hi> peeviſhly diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not only that the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> an ignorant heatheniſh people, but that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, whom <hi>I</hi> believe their conſcience tels them are many of them honeſt, periſh not.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They are diſcontented at the <hi>Parliament;</hi> let their expreſſions, papers, peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſecret charges, open accuſations againſt them, becauſe their hands are not embrued in the blood of their friends and ſervants, that God hath honoured, even in their blood, who have been at all times willing to ſacrifice it freely for them, witneſſe this truth,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>At the people that heare them, entertaine them, or give them any lodging, houſe or harbour,</hi> witneſſe Mr <hi>Prinnes</hi> late Chatechiſme, Mr. <hi>Edwards Gangre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> ſuch uncharitable men, are they even ſo far void of good nature, as to ſuffer thoſe to famiſh for want, that under God, have been inſtruments to keep them alive.</p>
            <p n="4">4. At the <hi>Independents,</hi> to ſee them proſper, encreaſe, to be intruſted in any place military or civill, to heare any ſpeak for them, or ſee any to ſmile upon them, Oh how it grieves, vexes, diſcontents, and troubles them! as their late <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance</hi> declares: is it poſſible for them to ſleep for anger?</p>
            <p n="5">5. At <hi>themſelves,</hi> that their owne luſts, inordinate deſires are not ſatisfied; that they have not been induſtrious enough, that they have not ſate up longer, and riſen earlyer, to have invented ſome meanes to roote out the <hi>Independents</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113769:8"/>
If ſuch a ſociety and combination of perſons make up a faction, and are ſufficient alone, how Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> can cleare <hi>Presbytery</hi> from being a faction I know not: What will any one ſay, if I ſhew them many more and many worſe in their <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Aſſemblyes, I ſhall name but two more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>They are a bloody people,</hi> who thirſt after blood, who have bound themſelves with an oath, yea they have made <hi>the Proteſtation and Covenant</hi> to become bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy unto them, through their ſtrained and forced ſence of it, falſely ſurmiſing, it binds them to endevour the taking away of liberties, eſtates, and lives, of all that are in their judgements heretiques, &amp;c. But ſurely this was not the true intent of it, thus to ſet the Kingdome by the eares, for there is the ſame parity of reaſon, that the <hi>Independents</hi> ſhould endevour the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> deſtructions as on the contrary, judgeing them erronious; but if Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> tels me they have cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted to extirpate errour, hereſie and ſchiſme, I demand whether there is no way to baniſh errour and hereſie out of the Church, except the perſons of them that hold it be baniſhed out of the world? though he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not let them live in the Church with him, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not he be contented to let them alone in the world? O that he would tel me what meanes the Parable of ſuffering the tares &amp; wheat to grow together in the field till harveſt? he muſt either ſay the tares be hipocrites as ſome, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane perſons as others, but he cannot ſay they are hipocrites, for theſe are ſuch as may be knowne to be tares, therefore they muſt be perſons knowne to be contrary to ſound godlineſſe, either in judgement or practiſe. Now the queſtion is, where theſe perſons are to be ſuffered, and what is meant by the field, which is either the Church or the world;<note n="a" place="margin">Becauſe Col. Waſhington after M. <hi>Edwards</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Sermon in Chriſt-Church, oppoſed his expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of this Parable, a warrant was ſent for him from the Lord Major, and he bound to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſwer this (marvelous contempt) at the Seſſions.</note> but not the Church, for the mouthes of of heretiques muſt be ſtopped, and hereſie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe caſt forth, therefore it muſt be in the world, if ſo, let not Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> deceive himſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers any longer, by telling them they muſt be caſt out of all the chriſtian world; except he think there is none of the world in <hi>England, Scotland, France, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Spaine, Germany, Italy,</hi> and the like: Had he had but ſo much patience, a to have given the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament leave to have given their own interpretation of their owne words, he and his brethren would not ſo raſhly have accuſed them for breach of Covenant. But it is apparent their own words being the interpretation, they have taken an oath, and made it bloody unto them And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are a <hi>prophane people</hi> What is the matter of their National Church, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtones, or dead rubbiſh? Or is it not a ſtrange compoſition of dea h &amp; life, hell and Heaven, light and darkneſſe, Chriſt and Beliall, good and evill? How are their Nationall, how are their parochiall Churches conſtituted, but by being borne in ſuch a Kingdome, or ſuch a peice of ground which wee know naturally brings forth nothing but thiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and evill weeds? I confeſſe could <hi>I</hi> ſee a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or a pariſh ſo cleane as to bring forth nothing but holy fruit, could <hi>I</hi> ſee men borne Saints, and the Kingdome of Earth convert men as ſoone as they are in it, or could <hi>I</hi> heare a voyce from Heaven ſaying, Oh England, or the like, <hi>I</hi> take thee and all perſons in theeto be a peculiar nation to my ſelf, above all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113769:9"/>
all that are borne in thee ſhal be holy, I would plead for a National Church too, but in the mean time they cannot excuſe their Temples from being founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an ill foundation, built up with rotten timber, and adorned with a fading glory; their garden from being ſowne with il ſeed, and bringing forth evill fruit, if all theſe ſorts of people can but prove a faction, ſure <hi>I</hi> am they are the greateſt in England; and let them not cry out the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, while their hands are full of blood, let them not proclaim a feaſt to take away <hi>Naboths</hi> Vinyard. But if he &amp; his bretheren ſhal ſay I wrong them, by laying this to their charge, that their Church is a meere compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of light and darkneſſe, of bloody and prophane men and the like, let them but anſwer me in theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether or no, all that live in their pariſh, and frequent their aſſemblies, having been chriſtned (as they terme it) when they were infants, be not mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their Church?</hi> If he ſay not, <hi>I demand when they were excluded?</hi> if he ſaith they were never of it, <hi>I deſire he would not plead for a Nationall Church, nor power to ſuſpend and excommunicate, for the Church hath nothing to doe to judge thoſe that are without, ſeing there is ſo many in the Kingdome that were never of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether or no all that are of their aſſemblyes, are ſuch that in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences they can believe all pertake of the divine nature, that they are all Saints? Or whether or no there are not among them prophane, groſſe, Ignorant, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, ſuperſtitious, and blood-thirſty people, yea even Atheſts, men of no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion at all, Caviliers, murderers &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether or no I have ſaid truth or not, in ſaying the matter of their Church is not purely chriſtian, but antichriſtian?</hi> Of theſe Queſtions I expect an anſwer from Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it appeares clearely if theſe ſorts of people prove a faction, and a faction preceds ſudden deſolation; then it is high time for the Presbyterians to repent, weepe and lament, for their deſtruction is at hand: But I come to his 6. <hi>Symtome</hi> that preaches ruine to them he ſtiles Independets, Anababtiſts &amp;c. which he ſaith is.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>There reaching after, and medling with all kind of perſons and things, graſping of all at once, labouring to engroſſe all offices, and places of power into their hands, ſlighting and abuſing all that ſtand in their way:</hi> Wil Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> never ceaſe thus ſubtilly to incenſe the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> againſt faithful ſubjects, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make them believe, they would wreſt the ſword out of their hands, &amp; ſet up another King, Oh what a bitter incendiary appears here! even ready if he can to ſet the world on fire. But I to haſten, muſt turne the glaſſe to himſelfe, and his bretheren, that by a direct reflection they may know themſelves in their proper colours. Who meddles with all kind of perſons and things like them? With Kings and Parliaments like them? With Townes, Cities, Countries, and Kingdoms like them? Who endevours to get more power into their hands then they? Who complain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſo much for want of power as they? All their bookes, petitions, pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, and Remonſtrances, declare them to be the moſt impatient people under the ſunne, till they have a ſword put into their hands, till the Parliament become their ſervants (I had almoſt ſaid their vaſſals) thy care not who they diſcontent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113769:9"/>
ſo they pleaſe themſelves, whether it be Parliament, Army, or Kingdoms; M. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> hath given the world a full accompt of ſuch a ſpirit, in that infectious <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavilian</hi> Epiſtle to his <hi>Vlcerous</hi> Treatiſe, where he incites them to petition and petition againe, never to lye from the Parliament dores petitioning, what ever comes of it. If this be a <hi>Symtome</hi> of deſtruction I feare it will be woe daies with them. But I come to the 7. <hi>Symtome</hi> of their ruine which;</p>
            <p>M <hi>Edwards</hi> ſaith <hi>is the Sectaries great ſins and wickedneſſe &amp;c.</hi> That there are great ſins among Sectaries I deny not, but that he hath proved all thoſe he ſtiles <hi>Independents Anabaptiſts</hi> &amp;c. to be Heretiques, &amp; Schiſmatiques, I deny it, and it remaines for him to prove, when he knowes how, which I am confident will not be in this age. But he goes on largely to innumerate ſeverall, filthy and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable practiſes, and many untruthes, and fathers them upon the <hi>Independents,</hi> without any diſtinction. I ſhall chiefly ſpeak to two, the firſt is <hi>blood guiltineſſe in deſtroying, the lives of many by dipping, weakly and antient perſons in Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in cold ſeaſons.</hi> If Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> can prove what he ſayes, it will ſave him from being reputed the father of this untruth, ſurely if he had knowne the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that had killed any, or the perſons that was killed, the world ſhould have heard of it long before now, he wants neither wil nor malice to declare any thing that may render them odious. To prove his generall concluſion he produces a particular of a ſtory of one <hi>Oates,</hi> that dipped a young woman who ſwelled with the water, ſhee received into her, which water ſome report was found in her after ſhee was dead, others ſay <hi>Oates</hi> drowned her: O miracle! O wonder! O prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie! A woman drowned, living twenty dayes after ſhee came forth of the water. If M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſaith ſhee, came by her death by it, that is as monſtrus to me as the other, ſhee was as well nine dayes after ſhee had been in the water, as ſhee had been a great while before. But he ſaith it is reported, ſhee confeſſed it to be the cauſe of her death. O, what wil not envie ſay, if her cleering the man &amp; the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter from being the cauſe of her death, can by any Logick or Sophiſtrie be ſaid to accuſe them, then the report is true, otherwiſe it is but a winter ſtorie, and falſe report, beſides the young womans own mother came to <hi>London</hi> to cleare the man; for the truth is, the woman dyed of a Dropſie, the water of which was found within her after her death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But if any ſhall conceive this to be water ſhee received into her when ſhee was in the water, it being twenty dayes after, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe, but judge ſuch a mans intellectualls ſcarce ſound, and whereas he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the Juſtices ſent him to the Gaole, the truth is (as <hi>I</hi> am informed) the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices would not medle with it, But the Coroner ſent him thither by his owne warrant, if Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſayes he doth not affirme it to be a truth, that either <hi>Oates</hi> or the water killed her, which is his beſt courſe, ſince they cannot prove <hi>Oates</hi> baptized her, but is only a report and cannot prove ſuch a thing, ever let him repent of his untruths and poſſitive affirmations of ſome to be ſo killed, for page 188. of the ſecond part of <hi>Gangrena,</hi> he boldly charges them with bloody guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe in that particular, let him not vent heareſayes for oracles any more.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe one that had been dipped ſhould have dyed, ſoone after in much leſſe ſpace then twenty dayes, muſt the water neceſſarily have killed her. For my part I can conceive no reaſon for it, but let him and his brethren of the <hi>Tribe of Levi</hi> looke back and conſider how many poore <hi>Infants</hi> without there conſent they have ſprinkled being ſick and wel nigh halfe dead in peoples eſtimation, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113769:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
would they take it well, if any ſhould endict them for killing their infants? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they would be eſteemed ridiculous, yet for ſuch a practiſe is there as much ground to frame an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndictment, and more then for the other; Let M. <hi>Edwards</hi> bring better proofes hereafter for his accuſations, or elſe let all his friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that love him, perſwade him to leave glorying in his ſhame for the future.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Article materiall is [he ſaith] <hi>they uſe all wayes and meanes in their power, to engage the two Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons in a Warre, one againſt the other;</hi> Let M. <hi>Edwards</hi> now bring forth his witneſſes, and make good his Charge if he know how: Had he but halfe ſo much colour to charge the <hi>Independants, &amp;c.</hi> to be inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndiaries between the two Kingdomes, as I have againſt him, he had ſome proofe for what he hath written.</p>
            <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſecond part of his <hi>Gangrena</hi> tels me, that he hath either received infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the <hi>Scots</hi> are reſolved to engage themſelves againſt a party at leaſt of this K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gdome, and that a conſiderable one, or he would have it ſo, elſe what meanes that expreſſion of his <hi>page</hi> 193. viz. <hi>God will honour our bretheren of Scotland, to make them a great meanes of their failing,</hi> [ſpeaking of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants</hi>] <hi>and they ſhall fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l before the Scots, as the Prelatical &amp; Popiſh party did,</hi> marke, how did they fall before the <hi>Scots;</hi> they came in a hoſtile manner, &amp; was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed. See if all you that take notice of his expreſſions, cannot eaſily view his ſpirit, painted in great red letters; he ſaith further, <hi>page</hi> 194 <hi>God will make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> come</hi> (v z.) <hi>the Sectaries, Anabaptiſts, Independants, that whole Faction, and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p before their feet</hi> (viz) the Scots, <hi>that is, they ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, and triumph over theſe Sectaryes;</hi> a little after in the ſame <hi>page,</hi> ſpeaking ſtill of the <hi>Scots,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>thou ſhalt have victory over thy enemies, and thou ſhalt enrich thy ſelfe with their ſpoiles,</hi> he tels the world that the Scots ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be notable Plunderers, and have the Pillage of the field: will the <hi>Scots</hi> thank him for this? To all which I ſhall only reply thus much; He may be deceived, for God fruſtrateth the token of the Lyars, and maketh Diviners mad, and turneth wiſemen backward, <hi>Eſay</hi> 44.25. But he goeth on and ſaith, <hi>they are guilty of prophaneſſe, looſenes of life, carnall confidence, and the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke;</hi> I have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar d what prophaneſſe is amongſt the <hi>Presbyterian-Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h members,</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding J have not yet heard of one excommunicated ſince the Biſhops times, but wheras he blames for carnall confidence, J wonder he bluſhes not to ſay ſo, let me tell him of their carnall confidence, it is ſo great, that for ought J can ſee moſt of them have no other; how do they cry out for a ſword of Steel to be their helpe) they call upon Priſons, Fines, Baniſhments, Confiſcation, of Goods, Fire and Faggot to helpe them, or they are undone, when theſe that he termes <hi>Independants,</hi> having Truth on their ſide, they knowing truth defends them, dare appeare in the middeſt of Wolves, Lyons and Beares, without an arme of fleſh; and the other ſhrouds themſelves under Monarchy, ſecular Authority, and will go no further then they will accompany them. If great ſins and wickednes is a forerunner of ſudden deſtruction, it is time for the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to looke about them; but I come to his eighth and laſt ſymptom.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Which he ſayth is, <hi>their not being moved to repentance, when God hath teſtifyed againſt them, and ſpit in their faces, as by laying open their nakednes, and fully diſcovering their wayes, by ſome Bookes written, by ſtirring up the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113769:10"/>
City of LONDON againſt them, but rather blaspheme the more, and not beene humbled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath God dealt thus with them, and they made theſe returnes to him? J can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe it, but I ſee the main thing is, when God hath diſcovered any infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to them, they have not teſtifyed their humility and repentance to him and his bretheren; is there no confeſſion but auricular? Is there no humiliation but in their preſence? But this is an uſuall thing in his dialect to ſpeak what comes uppermoſt; I adviſe him ſeriouſly to examine his own heart, and the truth of what I have declared and manifeſted, and let him tell me whether their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is not great, and the covering of it but Figge leaves; it may be he will once ſpeake truth, and confeſſe their ſinnes and evill wayes, appeares as <hi>Sodom and Gomorah;</hi> but yet he hath a ſalve to apply to his ſore, a hole to creep out at, he may perhaps ſay, they keep dayes for faſting and humiliation for their ſinfull nakednes, and ſpirituall and carnall abominations: But if he can thus blind the eyes of men, yet the <hi>Al-ſeeing God,</hi> ſees that great hypocriſie that lurkes under their Faſts, are they the more humble becauſe they abſtain from bread? Doe they thinke that God is well pleaſed with their faſting, when they faſt for <hi>ſtrife and debate,</hi> and their hearts and hands are full of bloud? Is this their humiliation, is this Evangellicall Repentance? Is this the Faſt that God hath choſen; The proclayming of a Faſt will not excuſe <hi>Ahabs</hi> taking away <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, and his life too. He ſaith God hath diſcovered <hi>the Independents nakednes,</hi> ſurely, M. <hi>Edwards</hi> much forgot himſelfe when he wrote this, <hi>God hath diſcovered their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering</hi> rather, hath not God made it manifeſt in the eyes of all People, that they are cloathed with ſo much honeſty, inocency, integrity, pyety, and courage, in all their undertakings, that it is impoſſible for him to uncover them, though he endeavours it all he can.</p>
            <p>Surely, Gods dealing hath been ſo plain, that if their eyes were not ſhut, they would ſee God going before them, by a cloud by day, and a pillar by night, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring them before the People, giving them favour, notwithſtanding his and his brethrens conſtant endeavours to deſtroy them, the more they have en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to deſtroy them, the more they have encreaſed, though they, like cruell taske-maſters have end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avoured to make their worke, their bondage and miſery great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and their ſtrength and helpe leſſe, yet God hath the more multiplyed them, crowning their enterprizes with ſucceſſe, and that great and wonderfull. Mee thinks M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould do well ſeriouſly to conſider, how God hath made his and his bretherens wrath to praiſe him, and the remainder of their wrath he hath reſtrained; while they have endeavoured to ſwallow them up all greedily, with a <hi>Petition, a Remonſtrance, gangrenous Diſcourſe,</hi> and <hi>virulent Sermon,</hi> God hath turned all into good for them, and they are yet delivered: And M. <hi>Edwards</hi> is angry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> peeviſh, and much diſcontented; thus, though God hath diſcovered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to themſelves, and ſhewed them their vanity in fighting againſt God, they ſhut their eyes and will not ſee: have they been humbled? have they repented for this evill, of perſecuting amd curſing whom God bleſſeth, even of their fighting againſt God? Surely no: but they blaſpheme the more, <hi>their throats are even ſcorched with great heat,</hi> thirſting after the bloud of the Saints, and the Prophets, <hi>but they repent not, to give God the glory, though the Kingdome is full of darknes, yet
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113769:11"/>
they repent not of their evill deeds.</hi> Rev. 16.9, 10, 11. They are envious at the proſperity of the Righteous, there is not one victory, one mercy, one priveledge beſtowed upon the <hi>Independants,</hi> but they murmur at it and ſeek to turne it about to their deſtruction, and this is tho fruit of Gods diſpenſation. Tell me, after their faſtings thus many yeares, which of them is more meeke and humble then they were before they began? Oh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow many of them faſt for ſtrife and debate, and ſmite with the Fiſt of wickednes! Thus now, if continuing in ſin, not repent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting at the diſcovery of their nakednes, be a ſign of ruine, or if any other of all his Symptomes, have propheſied deſolation, all wiſe men may ſee to what paſſe they are brought, in what a ſad, wofull deplorable, and lamentable condition the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are in.</p>
            <p>But leaſt M. <hi>Edwards</hi> Propheſy ſhould fayle him, he hath diſcovered a ſound reſerve, when he was in the Front of his Propheſy, not infallibly knowing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the words he had ſpoke would come to paſſe, he ſaith his Propheſie is true, <hi>if ever God ſpake by him;</hi> The great queſtion being yet unreſolved to me, and I believe many more, <hi>whether evre God ſpake by him or not?</hi> Thus he thinks to excuſe himſelfe from being eſteemed as, and adjudged for,, (whether he hath uttered a truth or a lye) a falſe Prophet; but I ſhall follow him a little further, and conſider ſomething of his other Corallaryes.</p>
            <p>In the third Corallary, he proceeds thus, <hi>Hence then from all theſe error, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, blaſphemyes, and practiſes of the Sectaryes, we may ſee what a great evill and ſin Separation is, from the communion of the Reformed Churches, and how highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God, for men to make a ſchiſme and rent in the Churches of God, in a time of Reformation, God puniſhing the ſchiſme and ſeparation of our times, with ſo many Hereſyes, Blaſphemyes, and wicked practiſes, &amp;c.</hi> It pityes me to ſee how the man through a miſtake, or ſomething worſe, hath wound himſelfe into a labyrinth; how he builds upon a rotten and ſlippery foundation; he charges the <hi>Independents</hi> with the guilt of ſchiſme, when it is yet to prove, that thirs is a true Church; could he prove their Nationall or Parrochiall Churches, <hi>Goſpell Temples,</hi> true ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all houſes, built upon a right foundation, in a right Goſpell forme, by a Goſpell Miniſtrie, then had he a ground for his charge, but if he cannot prove them ſuch, <hi>(Jure d vino)</hi> by the ballance of the Sanctuary, and yet can prove them true Churches, and the <hi>Independents</hi> guilty of ſchiſme <hi>erit mihi magnus Apollo;</hi> If they cannot prove themſelves true Churches, will not their leaving of them be a plain diſcovery of their true obedience in hearkning to the Spirits call, to come forth of <hi>Babylon?</hi> If he ſayes, though for the preſent they are not as they deſire, and as they hope they ſhall be, but they are now reforming, I anſwer, tis true, he ſpeakt much, and writes much, of Reformation of their Church, and the like; ô how it grieves my heart to ſee his Head full of gray haires, and yet he knowes it not, they have more need to looke to their foundation, then to talke of Reformation, for if that be not firm, the building connot be right; the truth is, it is the heigth, depth, breadth, and length of folly, to be at much paines and coſt, to beautify the out ſide, when the inn-ſide is full of corruption of dead mens bones; this is but healing a wound at the top, when it is feſtered and full of corruption within, all the Reformation of their Church, without a ſequeſtration, without a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>undation, is but as if a man that was ſick at heart ready to dye, ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113769:11"/>
ſend for a Chirurgeon to take away ſome Warts from his hands: or like an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe man that layes a foundation of glaſſe, hay or ſtubble, and erects a very faire ſpecious, and beautifull pallace upon it, which preſently falls down for want of a good foundation, and the builders labour, care and treaſure is but loſt; ſuch a foundation every one hath juſt cauſe to feare theirs is, and like to it will be their Reformation. How long therefore will it be before Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ceaſe to call evill good and good evill, light darkneſſe and darkneſſe light; O the conſideration of the former Symptoms, as they are faithfully applyed, clear the <hi>Independents</hi> from the guilt which M. <hi>Edwards</hi> r pen caſts upon them, &amp; ads a luſter to their practiſe, it commends it, it proclaimes them moſt happy that are come forth from their confuſed aſſemblyes, as being come into a City of refuge. Al the dirt that he throwes in the faces of them whom he accuſeth of Schiſme, will never ſtick, but be like a drop of cold water powred on a ſtraw, that falls from it without leaving the leaſt impreſſion behind it: If he and all his Brethren ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally or aſſembled together, ſhould plot, ſtudy, conſpire, and endeavour to prove them guilty of Schiſme from a true Church, becauſe from them, though they ſhould fill the world with Tractate after Tractate, Sermon after Sermon Petition after Petition, <hi>Gangrena</hi> after <hi>Gangrena<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp; Volume after Volvme, they would never be able to doe it; a third, nay a fourth <hi>Gangrena</hi> wil not effect it.</p>
            <p>Thus may thoſe who through the Spirit diſcerne the deepe things of God, ſee how dangerous it is to abide with them, where there is ſuch a ſtupidity, ſuch an unity, &amp; ſuch a harmony, in darkneſſe, that it may be juſtly ſuſpected truth is fallen in, or excomunicated out of their Churches.</p>
            <p>But he further tells us <hi>of many judgments of God againſt thoſe whom</hi> in his mouth are <hi>Schiſmatiques &amp;c. as ſeparation from God;</hi> his words need explanation, or it may be well judged he is <hi>Armin us</hi> his friend: But my thinks he ſhould have been ſilent in this, that a little before ſaid <hi>their Brethren even their Brethren of</hi> Scotland <hi>have been afflicted with ſword and peſtilence,</hi> Thus <hi>Incidit in Scyllam qui vult vitare Charybdin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For feare of comming nigh the <hi>Independents,</hi> he ſtumbles ſo often being out of his way, that it is to be feared he wil fal ſuddenly. I could tel of many heavy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their Congregations. <hi>A horrible</hi> &amp; <hi>wicked thing, the Prieſts propheſie lyes, and the people love to have it ſo,</hi> go into their Congregations, from perſon to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſee whether a worſe then <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe, hath not covered many nay moſt of their faces, enquire of them whether they have left their former Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition? Have they forgotten their bowing at the Altars, at the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> Their hoods and Surplices, their croſſes in their Chriſtenings, the common-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the like? Oh the unbeliefe! Oh the ſtupidity that hath ſeiſed upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaith <hi>Schiſme</hi> fom them hath <hi>Cains</hi> marke upon it, of a Fugitive and a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond; But I am ſure the very character of <hi>Ephraim</hi> is ſtamped upon them, they are full of gray haires, and know it not, or like <hi>Iſachar,</hi> couch downe under the burden of <hi>ignorance, pride and prophanneſſe, being Brethen neerly allyed to</hi> Simeon <hi>and</hi> Levie. But I paſſe to his.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Coroll.</hi> Which is full of high accuſations againſt the Parliament in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and many worthy members in particular, for ſleeping while the <hi>Devill</hi> ſowes hereſie; ſurely never was there more ſubtilty uſed, to incenſe an Honourable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113769:12"/>
Parliament againſt a loyall and honeſt people, and the people againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament then in his books, or elſe what meanes his publiſhing them to the world, even to their friends and enemyes, to be careleſſe dreamers, ſleepers, that while they ſhould like Maſtives, have given warning of Theeves approaching, they have been dumbe, drunk, of faſt a ſleepe. Taxing many of them, for endevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all they can to hinder the eſtabliſhment of Religion, threatning them with heavy judgements.</p>
            <p>Will he and his Brethren never be contented till the Parliament become their ſervants, and ſlaves, to execute their <hi>Mandates,</hi> to propagate their deſignes, their private intereſts, though the Kingdome periſhes? God hath hitherto bleſſed his people under them; I hope he will doe ſo ſtill, by filling them with the ſpirit of wiſdome, counſell, underſtanding, and the feare of the Lord, that they may judge not according to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> but according to truth.</p>
            <p>He ſaith <hi>their Miniſters have been aſleepe,</hi> I think now he ſpeakes the truth, he might have added, and are a ſleepe ſtill, elſe they could not chuſe but ſee whence their pedegree is derived, even as farre as <hi>Rome,</hi> where their plots are laid, even in the botomleſſe pit of darkneſſe, and thither they all tend, even in the end to their owne ruine; and tbat their parochiall Churches have lineally deſcended not from Chriſt, but from Antichriſt, and their maintenance by <hi>Tythes</hi> to be an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix to the Leviticall Prieſt-hood, aboliſhed by the death of Ghriſt.</p>
            <p>He ſaith <hi>the people have been a ſleepe too,</hi> it ſeemes even so; or why are they ſtill deluded with their ſpecious pretences of piety, learning and the like, when others can diſcern wolues under ſheepes clothing? or why do they take their words for oracl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, their examples for preſidents, their canons &amp; lawes for Scripture? but that their eyes are cloſed, they are even faſt a ſleepe, but I proceed to his 5. <hi>Corollary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. He aſcend, to a ſtrong exhortation, <hi>to all thoſe that have ſeparated from them to returne to them, with two ſubtle inſinuations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. ſaith he, <hi>ſome have been only deceived, but are honeſt, and for-ſook us for more pure preaching;</hi> one while he ſayes Independency is a faction, and makes them all ſeem to appeare to be Schiſmatiques, and Heretiques, but lo, to advance his owne end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they are honeſt men, I ſuppoſe he remembred his expreſſions in the ſixt Reaſon of his book againſt toleration page 29. where he ſaith, <hi>In many if not in moſt Townes and Pariſhes it cannot be helped, but that there are and will be for many yeares men of no great popular gifts for preaching; who alſo according to their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, not having been brought up to it, cannot ſo comply with their people, Now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that live in theſe pariſhes (ſeing they may keepe ther houſes and places of abode) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the newes af a toleration, will for the benefit of more powerfull, practicall and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous preaching, betake themſelves to go to their Churches, and ſo will fall to their principles, and ſo we ſhall have upon this ground ſwarmes of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He confeſſeth, for more pure preaching they forſooke them, and yet bluſhes not to exhort them to returne back again Be theſe your Goſpell exhortations, O it, much pities me to ſee how people are deluded by them, have they all been at Vniverſityes? are great ſchollers, Orthodox<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Divines, and good church-men? now therefore they think the world muſt needs wonder after them, and then in the next place, he inſinuates that divers have been regained, as <hi>Johannes Denkins, Obbo. Philppus</hi> &amp;c, <hi>us.</hi> If this may be a ground to believe more wil returne to them,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113769:12"/>
it may more ſtrongly be turned upon them, as aground to believe more will come from them, that have been long deluded by them, becauſe ſome eminent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, are come from them, and cannot by any meanes be deluded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to them, yea ſome of the Prieſts are become obedient to the faith, which is a wonder; but he inforces his exhortations yet more violently, and ſaith.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Stay no longer in the way of Schiſme, leſt God let thee goe further,</hi> thus he takes that for granted <hi>(viz)</hi> that the Independents are in the Schiſme, though as it is apparent before, he cannot prove it, ſo that the ſtrength of this exhortation falls with his former diſcourſe; But ſeeing they cannot acquit themſelves from Schiſme from Chriſt, from the Goſpell and Ordinances of Chtiſt, I deſire all may ſee whether they are going, and into what they are falen, and repent and come forth of Babylon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith <hi>the Independent Church way, is a way of error &amp; confuſion that God never bleſſed with edification, oneneſſe of heart.</hi> The falſhood af this is truly and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten declared by many members of ſeparated Churches, who bleſſe God for their edification by and in the communion each with other, in the Father and the Sonne.</p>
            <p>But are they all of one mind amongſt them? thats ſtrange if they be, is it not the combynation of <hi>Ephrim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſah,</hi> to be both againſt <hi>Iudah?</hi> To <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize Juſtones?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what edification is there amongſt them? Doe they build up one another in faith, love, me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſſe, gentleneſſe, long-ſuffering forgiving and forbearing? If they did, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir ſpirit would not be ſo violent, they build; its true, but what? A bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuperſtructure, under the name of zeale upon a ſlippery foundation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He advances yet further ſaying, <hi>Come out of her, leſt you partake of their ſins and plagues.</hi> It is concluded by him, that the Independents muſt be baniſhed the Chriſtian world (I would he would tell me what he meanes by it) The greateſt ſin, and the greateſt plague, that I can or may deſire any to come forth from, is darkneſſe, which darkneſſe walkes round about their high places at noone day, O therefore I ſay now to them all that ſhall come forth, come forth ſtay no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hoodwinked, let no man beguile you and deceive you, what though you looſe credit and eſteeme in the world and the like, care not: God is all things in one, and one thing in all things, yea he is that one that is all things; I long till you be made partakers of the glorious light of the Lord Jeſus, that in his light, and not in another you may ſee light. I now come to his.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And laſt <hi>Coroll.</hi> where he tels us <hi>there is a great difference betweene his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren the</hi> Scots <hi>and the Independents,</hi> I could tell of much difference betweene them indeed, but I forbeare, becauſe I love peace. He ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>the</hi> Scots <hi>have been trve to their principles,</hi> wherein he accuſeth the Independents that they have not been true to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; But let Mr. <hi>Edwads</hi> tell me, have not the Independents been true to their principles? Speakes he in earneſt? In what have the Independents been falſe to their principles in all the engagements of their deareſt lives, their principles being the Kingdoms peace, knowing that <hi>Salus Populi</hi> is SUPREMA LEX, they have adhered to them, as their actions and ſucceſſe declares. They are a people that in deſpite of envy, have and will appeare, (I am confident) in faithfulneſſe, integrity, courage and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113769:13"/>
to the Parliament to have exceeded many, but come behind none.</p>
            <p n="1">1. he ſaith, <hi>the Scots have improved and made uſe of all victories, ſucceſſes, and advantages, for the good of both Kingdomes,</hi> but he ſaith (in a paſſion ſurely) <hi>that the Independents have not, but have ſpoken againſt the Scots:</hi> Oh that he did but remember that ſaying, <hi>Qui alterum incuſat furti ipſum ſe intueri oportet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He condemnes the Independents for ſpeaking againſt the Scots; but when will he condemne himſelfe, and his Bretheren for ſpeaking againſt the Independents<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I could tell what uſe ſome have made of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir victories when they have had any, but I had rather heale then make differencs: But have not the Independents made uſe of their victories for the good of the State? the good uſe they have made of their victories, appeares.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that they have improved every victory, not delaying but proſecuting it to the utmoſt, they were not like <hi>Pompey</hi> that knew how only to conquer, but not to make uſe of a victory, but as God hath made them famous in conquering, ſo in purſuing every victory; I might evidence this from the battle at <hi>Naſby</hi> to this day, had all done ſo it had been well; and I am confident many groanes, ſighs and teares had been ſpared.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In their mercifulneſſe and kindneſſe to the Country, being victoris in that they did not pillage, pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder and deſtroy, and would lye no longer in any place then neceſſity conſtrayned them, and all becauſe they would not be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have made this uſe of their victories, to ſay in ſeeing, and ſee in ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God hath gone out before them, crowning their indevours, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his inſtruments, with continued ſucceſſe, as many victories teſtifie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in all theſe, they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired God might be gloryfied, whoſe glory will ſhine in and by them, when M. <hi>Edwards</hi> honour is buried in the grave.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith <hi>our Brethren the</hi> Scots <hi>have borne with much patience, infinite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches in City and in Country:</hi> If ſo, let M <hi>Edwards</hi> examine the reaſon, let him lend an eare as farre as <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> looſers will oft times ſpeake: But have not the Independents (whether his Bretheren or not it matters not much) under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone more reproaches, &amp; with much more patience? Have they not been called by the Presbyterians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea by the leading men of them, Villains, Heretiques, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, Blaſphemers and the like? Have they not cryed out to the Magiſtrate to ſuppreſſe them, and in the meanetime I know them whom he calls Independents, Anabaptiſts, Heretiques and the like, have been praying for them, and have never yet put up one Petition to the Parliament to ruine them. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>the</hi> Scots <hi>have been forward moving for peace and ſettlement for the Chuch:</hi> Whenzeale and knowledge walke hand in hand, and ttuth leads them in the ſtraight path of love, we ſhall be free from jealouſies.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and his Bretheren, have condemned the Independents for being forward to ſettle the Church, and commends the <hi>Scots</hi> for it: I hope guiles, daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and diſſembling, will not thus alwaies paſſe for currant coyne; certainly the ſuperſcription of diſſimulation, is ſtamped upon theſe expreſſions: But have not the Independents been forward to ſettle the Church? certainly then they doe ill to rayle againſt them for making too much haſt. Have they not been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for peace? Oh ſtrange! When Envie, Pride, Avarice, malice and diſcontent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113769:13"/>
drive men they muſt need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> run: Why have the Independents fought thus long made ſuch haſt, ſacrificed ſo much blood, expoſed themſelves to ſo much hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, if not for peace? Let the effect of their worke, let that peace the Kingdome enjoyes within little more then twelve moneths laſt paſt, more then in many yeares before, ſpeake for them, for I may well hold my peace: Theſe ſtrange ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions make me much incline to believe one blood runs in his and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therens vaines, that run in theirs who ſaid of the victory at <hi>Marſton Moore,</hi> ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wee had had no victory, then the Independents ſhould have obtained it, and the glory of it,</p>
            <p>Thus having in generall examined and impartially reflected his prophecy wherein is the ſubſtance of both books contained, I ſhall proceed a little further to examine ſomthing more paricularly. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſtory of Captaine <hi>Hobſon,</hi> wherin is many charges drawne up againſt him, eſpecially concerning his preaching at <hi>Newport-Paganell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> In the ſecond e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt part of <hi>Gangrena</hi> Mr. <hi>Edwards ſaith;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paul Hobſon <hi>Preached in</hi> Newport-Paganell <hi>and thereabouts, in contempt of the Ordinance of Parliament made laſt</hi> April, <hi>after he was once taken and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned for it, and let go, be comes againe and does it the ſecond time, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Governour of</hi> Newport Paganell <hi>that then was, and misbehaved himſelfe.</hi> If one may judge of the reſt of his ſtories by this one paſſage, I poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirme them all falſe, for to my owne knowledge, after he was queſtioned for Preaching, when he returned he did not Preach againe, neither did he come back in contempt of the Governour, but for ſome armes taken from a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with him, and left at <hi>Newport,</hi> where he ſtayed but a litle while; therefore when Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> affirmes this for truth; it is no wonder though he is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to call light darknes, and darkneſſe light, he Quotes M. <hi>Pryns</hi> freſh diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of new lights to prove his ſtory, I have ſearched that, &amp; find no ſuch expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it: Surely Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath a quick invention: But it may be he will think to put off this well enough (as he hath done many things elſe) by ſaying thats but circumſtantiall, if he ſaith ſo, let me tell him, he that feares not to vent Circumſtances out of a malicious braine, which are evidently falſe, will not ſtick at telling ſubſtantiall untruthes: But<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for my part what ever he thinkes, I know it to be as ſubſtantiall an untruth as ever was declared, and many more know it as well as I: But Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> further (ſpeaking ſtill of Captaine <hi>Paul Hobſon</hi> and ſome with him, ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo when apprehended, uttering many bold and ſeditious ſpeeches, that they would acquaint their friends in the Houſe of Commons, of their bad uſage: That they were reſolved to make this buſineſſe, the leading caſe of the Kingdome, for all the godly party; adding, that if the godly and wel affected party, were thus perſecuted, they ſhould be forced to make a worſe breach then was yet, when they had done with the Kings party, and ſaying when they had made an end with the Caviliers, they ſhould be forced to raiſe a new warre, to fight with them</hi> Oh, what will not the Father of lyes perſwade ſome men to utter, and others to believe! the whole charge is compbonded of moſt notorious unjuſt, injurious and malitious flanders: But for the Readers further ſatisfaction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſhall give the world a full account of the ſtory, not varying a haires breadth from the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113769:14"/>Captaine <hi>Hobſon,</hi> with another Captaine going to Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Army; through <hi>Newport-Paganell,</hi> being in their way, they called there to ſee ſome of their former acquaintance, who earneſtly ſolicited them to ſtay a while with them, and deſired Captaine <hi>Hobſon</hi> to declare what God had cauſed him to enjoy of himſelfe (a harmleſſe pactice, not long ſince commended by the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians) which he accordingly did, and that without any moleſtation, or tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult; none oppoſing or queſtioning him, for what he had done. His exerciſe being finiſhed, the Captaine peaceably departed out of the Towne, and went to the Army; having diſpatched their buſineſſe there, they returned, and called at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> as they came back; where Captaine <hi>Hobſon</hi> was importuned to ſtay awhile, and accordingly he did, where ſome of his friends came to him, and deſired that they might ſpend ſome time together, in bleſſing God for that great victory God had given to Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> at <hi>Naſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bye:</hi> This was on the Saterday, the next day (being the firſt day of the weeke) they were unwilling to meet in the Town, for feare of diſturbance, ſo they went to <hi>Lathbury,</hi> where they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de both ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily and religiouſly. In the after-noone come ſome ſcattering Souldiers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that made a great diſturbance, by their fearefull ſwearing, horrid blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, horrible curſing, holding up a hound by the ears, to the window of the houſe, where the people met, &amp; bringing a pack of hounds full cry about the houſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in ſo much that Captaine <hi>Hobſon</hi> and ſome others went out to them, &amp; asked them by what warrant they made that diſturbance, they ſaid they had none, but would go fetch one from the then Governour of <hi>Newport,</hi> to that Captain <hi>Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> replyed, he would be ready to obey any order from him, and told him where he ſhould be in the evening, ready to anſwer any thing that ſhould be objected againſt him, the Souldiers were ſomthing pacified to heare him ſay ſo, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after comes one Enſigne <hi>Fiſh</hi> with aguard of <hi>Muſquetieres</hi> to apprehend them all, and carry them to the mayne Guard, ſaying the <hi>Governour</hi> ſent him, the Captaine deſired to ſee his warrant, the Enſigne told him, twas not the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> himſelfe but the Major that ſent him. But the Captaine and the reſt of the company, went peaceably along with the Guard, to the maine Guard, being ſhamefully abuſed by the way, yet reviling none, when they came to the mayne Guard, they abode there peaceably, A while after a Lieutenant came and told the company they might depart, but the Captaine deſired a warrant from the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for their peaceable departure, that they might not be moleſted by the rude multitude, but preſently came Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Cockaine,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ber,</hi> one of the Committee, and ſaid they came from the Governour, to teſtifie they had liberty to depart, ſaying they were ſorry that ſuch Gentlemen ſhould be ſo abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, being contrary to the Governors knowledge; ſo the priſoners were ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; departed from the maine Guard: But a while after the Captaines being with the Governour, they humbly deſired his honour to certifie them whether he gave any warrant for the practiſe of them that had ſo abuſed them, for if they did it contrary to his knowledge, they deſired Juſtice, He returned them this anſwer, he would doe them Juſtice, for he would ſend them with his Marſhall to Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> for he told them, they had run from their Colours, upon that, one of the Captaines produced his diſcharge, under Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his owne hand, which though the Governour would not read, yet Lieutenant Colonll <hi>Cockaine</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113769:14"/>
did and ſaid it was very authentirk, but Sir <hi>Samuel Luke</hi> the Governour ſaid they were lying fellowes, and he would not believe them whatſoever they ſaid, ſo he ſent them to the Army, by the Marſhall, Enſigne <hi>Fiſh</hi> and two Souldiers, and a friend of theirs, one that had been an eye and eare witneſſe to the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, accompanying them, and when they came thither, the Noble Generall examined the buſineſſe by a <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Warre,</hi> and it being faithfully reported to him, He wrot to Sir <hi>Samuel Luke</hi> to this effect;</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Have had the buſineſſe concerning thoſe Gentlemen you ſent to me, (Captain <hi>Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and Captaine <hi>B.</hi>) examined, and I find that they have been diſcharged of their Commands, at their owne importunity; the one by my ſelfe, and the other by the Colonell of that Regiment, the which if it had appeared to you (as they informed me they deſired to doe) I conceive it might have prevented any further trouble, either to you, or to my ſelfe in that buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p>It ſeemes their uſage, by thoſe who come a long withthem, hath been very uncivill, and diſhonorable unto Gentlemen, that have carried themſelves with fid lity and courage in this cauſe, and have been members of this Army, And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I can do no leſſe (without encouragement to ſuch ill carriages for the future, and for the ſatisfaction of thoſe Gentlemen) then deſire you to ſee full reparations made them by the Marſhall and the Enſigne, and that you c ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re them from their imployments.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your aſſured friend and Servant, THOMAS FAIRFAX.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Preſently after, the Captaines returned to <hi>Newport</hi> againe for their armes, which the Marſhall moſt abuſively had taken away (not in contempt, as Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> would have it) imediatly after their comming, Sir <hi>Samuel L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſent for them, &amp; when they came to him, he told them if he could not have Juſtice in the Army he would have it elſe where; &amp; asked them how long they intended to ſtay in Towne, they replyed, they would be gon preſently; he tould them he would ſend one along with them; they deſired to know whether he would ſend them as priſoners or not, he ſaid, not as priſoners; ſo they departed from him to a private houſe in Towne, where Captaine <hi>Oxford</hi> came to them to know if they were ready to go, they told him yes, only deſired ſo much liberty as to have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of one with them to <hi>London,</hi> who might if there ſhould be occaſion (from his owne knowledge) witneſſe the truth of things; but this being denyed them by the Governour, Captaine <hi>Hobſon</hi> ſaid, it ſeemed ſtrange to him, that their witneſſes might not be permitted to bear them company, ſaying theſe doings might poſſibly hinder a deſign that he had undertaken for the good of the State; But leaſt any ſhould wreſt his words, he deſired ſpeciall notice might be taken of his expreſſions, which was ſo done, ſo Captaine <hi>Oxford</hi> departed, ſaying God bleſſe you Gentlemen; and the Captaines preſently departed; not ſtaying to <hi>Preach,</hi> as Mr <hi>Edwards</hi> untruly, groundleſly, and unjuſtly affirmeth; Neither did they ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113769:15"/>
any ſuch mutinous, and ſeditious words, as are charged upon them. The truth of all which <hi>I</hi> have declared, is beyond and above all contradiction.</p>
            <p>Their Chriſtian meekneſſe and peaceable carriage, when they were firſt diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the rude multitude, like them that compaſſed <hi>Jaſons</hi> houſe; by their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid, helliſh bloody, and inſolent, rayling, ſwearing and curſing, with the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable practices of them that apprehended them at <hi>Lathbury</hi> is atteſted by <hi>Seventeene</hi> witneſſes, ſubſcribed with their owne hands.</p>
            <p>The certainty of their peaceable behaviour and demeanour at <hi>Newport,</hi> when, Captaine <hi>Oxford</hi> was with them, the vnjuſtneſſe, untruneſſe, and abominable falſity, of thoſe mutinous, ſeditious expreſſions Regiſtred by Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and M. <hi>Pryn</hi> is atteſted by divers that were eare witneſſes to the whole diſcourſe, that paſt between Captaine <hi>Hobſon</hi> and Captain <hi>Oxford</hi> (at that time, when thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions were falſly fathered on him) even by juſt perſons, fearing God, and of good report, and that under their owne hands.</p>
            <p>To ad one word more, there came nine witneſſes to London, to have atteſted the truth of the premiſſes, who earneſtly deſired that they might have been heard, but through ſome extraordinary occaſion could not.</p>
            <p>All thoſe writings ſubſcribed with their owne hands, I had publiſhed at large, but that I would not be too tedious: Thus have I impartially related the ſtory. But leſt Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould think to creep out of this hole, by ſaying Captaine <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Robert Ratford</hi> witneſſed it before the Parliament, and therefore ſhould ſtamp the ſuperſcription of truth upon it, becauſe out of the mouth of thoſe two men, I ſhal preſent a brief, yet ful and true diſcovery of what the witneſſes are, and then let all honeſt men judge, whether they are perſons ſit to be believed. Firſt for Captaine <hi>Oxford,</hi> he is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. One that is eminently knowne and noted, for his great ability to invent and publiſh untruths, among all that know him, and have the face of honeſty; his ingenuity and audacity, appeares in this, more then in any thing elſe, two or three untruthes at one time, were moſt boldly, and malitiouſly vented by him, before a cloud of witneſſes, in a Captaines houſe at <hi>Newport;</hi> So that through his cuſtome in this trade, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was at length famous (or rather imfamous) through his proverbe (when a thing ſounded void of ſence, reaſon, truth and equity) <hi>This is one of Oxfords lyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He is one that then neither feared God nor man (it would be the joy of my ſoule to heare he doth now) It is well known, he was not only drinking, but fighting at a Taverne, after nine a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ock at night, and was not long ſince put out of his Place to the joy of all there, that are faithfull friends to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p n="3">3- He is one very malicious, envious, and full of hatred; Who reported ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Captaine <hi>Hobſon,</hi> and another, that he could as willingly ſheath his ſword in their guts, as in the Cavaliers: Much more could I ſay, but I forbeare.</p>
            <p>If any one notwithſtanding, thinks I ſpeake as one poſſeſt with prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and ſo wrong him; Let him goe to <hi>Newport-Paganell,</hi> and inquire of all the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> that have but the face of godlyneſſe; And of all the <hi>Independents,</hi> whether I have wronged him or no? If Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> faith be ſo large as to believe him; I am confident he may believe any thing.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113769:15"/>2 As for <hi>Robert Ratford,</hi> that he is a common notorious lyar, ſwearer, curſer and prophane fellow, is atteſted by good hands; The teſtimony of a woman that was then, and is for ought I know ſtill a hearer in the <hi>Publique Aſſemblies of England;</hi> I will relate, who affirmes <hi>that this</hi> Robert Ratford <hi>came to the houſe of</hi> T. R. <hi>curſing, ſwearing, jeering, ſcoffing, villifying all that was there</hi> (viz.) <hi>in that houſe,</hi> where the Captain with ſome others were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended) <hi>like a mad man, running up and down the houſe, into the ſeverall roomes, puſhing under the beds, yet he was not ſatisfied, but his rage was ſo great, that when all the Souldiers and priſoners were gon, for the ſpace of one hour, he came back againe, and ſaid to her, You baſe whore, I could find in my heart, to pull your baſtard out of your armes, and kick it to peeces, ſwearing he could find in his heart to kick her,</hi> which he did, ſhee having her little child ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at her breſt: All this is atteſted under her hand: And this that he did and ſayd at his returne, the Lady <hi>A.</hi> living in the ſame towne, being by, can witneſſe it. A little while after, the ſame <hi>Robert Ratford,</hi> ſpeaking of one that was with Captain <hi>Hobſon</hi> when they were at <hi>Lathbury,</hi> ſaid, <hi>If ever I catch him Preaching, this ſword of myne ſhall cut him in peeces,</hi> and further ſaid, now the round-heads ſhall be hanged without any Law. There is a cloud of witneſſes, to prove the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable blaſphemie and prophaneſſe of him: Let Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſend, write, or go to <hi>Newport-Paganell,</hi> and fift out the truth of what I have ſaid, and print what he heares and no more; and <hi>I</hi> am confident in this, he and I ſhall agree.</p>
            <p>There was one other witneſſe that appeared at <hi>London</hi> againſt the Captaines who in my hearing, affirmed he never ſaw men carry themſelves more civilly, diſcreetly and orderly, in his life, and further affirmed to me in the Country, that he could witneſſe nothing againſt them, but bleſſed God he was with them, and when ſome broched moſt notorious untruths, he himſelfe ſaid they were lyes; this man was a <hi>Presbyterian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another witnes one <hi>Andrewes</hi> of Olney was ſummoned up to be one of Sir <hi>Samuell Lukes</hi> witneſſe, but he having declared he could not ſpeak any thing, but to cleare them, was ſent out of the towne, without giving any evidence at all This particuler, is worth ſerious conſideration.</p>
            <p>Having ſufficiently cleared this buſineſſe; I ſhall proceed to examine ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulers in Mr, <hi>Joſiah Rycrafts</hi> letter to Mr. <hi>Edwards;</hi> And concerning Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> teſtimony of him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the letter it ſelfe, it ſaith;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mr. Kiffen, <hi>and ſome other, upon their diſpute with Dr.</hi> Féatly, <hi>Mr</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy <hi>and ſome others, gave out to their members that they had the better, and Mr.</hi> Calamy <hi>durſt not diſpute with them.</hi> This Mr. <hi>Kiffen</hi> denyes: Till Mr. <hi>Rycraft,</hi> hath proved it, it will be judged but his ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That</hi> Kiffen <hi>was left out of that Diſputation, which was held, and to be held with Mr.</hi> Calamy. Mr. <hi>Rycrafts</hi> head is got in, needs muſt his body fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after; This is manifeſtly falſe: I call upon him to prove it: Mr. <hi>Kiffen</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red exemption, but it was not aſſented to,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That Mr.</hi> Kiffen <hi>was put to doe the drudgery, to fetch up members ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered to and fro the Country.</hi> This is allyed to the former relations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mr. <hi>Kiffen</hi> went not into the Country at all to fetch up any.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113769:16"/>4. He ſaith that not only <hi>Kiffen,</hi> but others alſo did the like good ſervice (as <hi>Hobſon</hi> the Taylor) in their places) This to my knowledge is an untruth. For Captain <hi>Hobſon</hi> ſtayed in the Town, to attend the diſpute.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He ſaith. <hi>That one</hi> Palmer, <hi>ſhould report Phiſitians left her, as they found her. An emphaticall untruth,</hi> For ſhee uſed no Phiſitian at all.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He tells a ſtory of <hi>a woman to</hi> be <hi>rebaptized:</hi> Surely he that durſt to affirm that, durſt affirme any thing, even the moſt horrible untruth in the world. But will any be ſo unwiſe to believe it, becauſe Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſaith it? His ſay-ſo, is no oracle to me; If it be, it is a falſe one, that ſpeakes ſeldome any thing but is either doubtfull, or an indubitable untruth.</p>
            <p>That which confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes my thoughts, and cauſes me to judge the man is not only guilty of thoſe untruths, but that his conſcience tells him ſo; is becauſe in his late <hi>Noſegay,</hi> he doth not ſo much as offer to prove one of theſe perticulers, which were all denyed before, by Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> Surely it argues fainthar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe, and a bad cauſe: What that valiant Mr. <hi>Rycraft,</hi> that threatens to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the workes of darkneſſe, ſhould be found bound in darkneſſe; bound with ſuch chaines, that neither wit, nor honeſty can break<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>! Is it poſſible? who would have thought it? Inſtead of anſwering them, behold a man-like ſpirit! he falls a rayling againſt Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> in a ſtrange diſtempered method; One would have thought the unhappineſſe of the man in ſtumbling ſo often before, in ſo few lines, ſhould have made him more cautious for the time to come, leſt in his next writing, he ſhould have quite fallen. But tis true,
<q>Naturam expellas ſurca tamen uſque recurrit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Convince him of one, he will preſently tell two more. Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> great boaſts of M. <hi>Rycrafts,</hi> is come to juſt nothing.</p>
            <q>Parturiunt montes naſcetur ridiculus mus.</q>
            <p>But to come to Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> teſtimony of the man to be <hi>Religious and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially affected to the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liament.</hi> If I knew what Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> meant by <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> I ſhould be able to ſay the more: But if he be Religious, light and love muſt declare it.</p>
            <p>But how that light or love may be ſeen in his ſpirit, that wrot that falſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious dark Letter, I cannot poſſibly ſee; its true (as <hi>I</hi> heare) the man hath ſome formality, a certaine kind of profeſſion (which is but very little) ſo hath the Kingdome, but they are never the more Chriſtians for that. Profeſſion is not poſſeſſion, formality is not Religion. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken to the teſtimony of Saint <hi>James,</hi> chap. 1. ver. 26. <hi>If any man among you ſeem to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart; this mans Religion is in vaine.</hi> It hath been Mr. <hi>Joſiah Ricrafts</hi> unhappineſſe in a ſuperlative degree, to have an unbridled tongue, and to be trading in the works of darkneſſe. He theatens a diſcovery of more deeds of darkneſſe; I confeſſe that he may ſoone doe, for yet <hi>I</hi> never ſaw any thing come under his hand, but had the impreſſion of darkneſſe upon it; and if he goes on in this ill courſe, the further the worſe.</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>cordiall affection to the Parliament,</hi> when he hath diſproved the Letter printed in Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> books, he may probably appear ſo. But if any man thinks he hath, in his <hi>Noſegay,</hi> I aſſure them, <hi>I</hi> can ſmell no ſuch ſavour in it. To ſpeake the beſt of his <hi>Noſegay,</hi> its but a vaine glorious gloſſe put upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113769:16"/>
a foule matter, but a ſheeps skin drawne upon a Wolves back. But to diſcover tis no other, let all men conſider with me a little what his <hi>Noſegay</hi> ſaith. Speaking of Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> he ſaith.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The man ſets his w t; on the tenter-hookes, how to be ſpatter Mr.</hi> Edwards <hi>or my ſelfe, with his tainted lyes, And to that end hath got a letter written to him, by an Anabaptiſticall Apprentice.</hi> Had Mr. <hi>Rycraft</hi> walked by the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of truth when he wrot this, he had never thus deſperately ſtumbled; certainly this beginning, preſages a bad cauſe, and as little ſtrength; The thing he ſpeaks is diametrically oppoſite to truth. The Letter was written to Mr. <hi>Kiffen,</hi> not to Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> except Mr. <hi>Rycraft</hi> or Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> have ſo much Sophiſtry as to prove Mr. <hi>Kiffen</hi> to be Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rycrafts</hi> ſtory will fall for want of of a prop. Neither did Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> get it written, but it came accidentally to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith (ſpeaking of the Author of the Letter to Mr. <hi>Kiffen) he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the ſaid Letter, to have more then ordinary acquaintance with me, which is well known to be as falſe as the Author of falſhood can invent.</hi> To whom is it well known that he hath not more then ordinary acquaintance with him? Is it to them in the ſame Family? Doe they know it is falſe? They know no ſuch thing; Who are the perſons that know it ſo well, I cannot imagine. Is it poſſible that he could live nigh four yeares together in one family with him, and not have more then ordinary acquaintance with him? Believe it who can; I have not faith to doe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>I will not deny, but that many times he hath intruded himſelfe into my company, my ſelfe knowing well enough, he was an abuſive fellow.</hi> It is no great matter to be called abuſive fellow, by him that cares not who he abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, neither feares whom he ſlanders. But I am ſory to ſee ſo much pride, in ſo few expreſſions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hee further proceedeth to manifeſt his inſolency, and arrogancy, as if he ſcorned any ſhould exceed or equalize him, ſaying;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have declared by my carriage, that I cared not for his company.</hi> Was this carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, this declaration, ſutable to a Goſpell Spirit, let wiſe men judge. <hi>Haman</hi> ſcorned a poore <hi>Mordecay,</hi> by his lofty proud carriage; Yet was <hi>Mordecay</hi> not the worſe, nor <hi>Haman</hi> the better.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He goeth on ſaying, <hi>He ſaith in the ſaid lying Letter, that I concealed a Colonell that came from the Kings Army, wich Colonell would have taken away the life of one Mr.</hi> Roberts, <hi>a worthy Miniſter, and ſaith if Mr.</hi> Roberts <hi>had known where he had been, he would endeavoured the hanging of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not this true? No, ſaith Mr. <hi>Rycraft,</hi> he asked Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> whether he knew of any ſuch Colonell, who anſwered him he knew no ſuch, neither did he know what the fellow meanes by naming ſuch a man as he never knew nor ſaw, Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mr. <hi>Rycraft</hi> knew not what he wrot, when he wrot this. aske Mr. <hi>Rycraft</hi> whether he did not uſe to call him Colonell? Whether he did not receive the Kings P ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re from him, &amp; ſaid it would ſecure him when the King came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> But the man thinks to evade it; for he ſaith <hi>he knew no ſuch man.</hi> Though he knew not ſuch a man as Colonell, yet he called him ſo. But the truth is (as I am credibly informed) he is a Lieutenant Colonell, his name is <hi>Anthony Diet:</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113769:17"/>
Can he deny this? Is he not his cozen? Surely tis true, it will be proved to his face. And for Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> his teſtimony; ſuch equivocation will not ſerve him, he knew him by the name of Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Anthony Diet</hi> at <hi>Brummingham.</hi> And can he deny but that this <hi>Anthony Diet</hi> ſought his life? Surely not without bluſhing. This vapouring will not excuſe Mr. <hi>Rycraft.</hi> Neither can Mr. <hi>Rycrafts</hi> letter to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> be any plea for him. None accuſed Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was in Towne. And let Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> if he can, deny that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e would have endevoured the hanging of him? But to proceed, Mr. <hi>Rycraft</hi> advanceth yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaying.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>And for his third lye, where he ſaith. I ſent money to one, to go to</hi> Oxford, <hi>the ſaid party nominated came lately to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> London, <hi>who affirmed to the lyeing Author his face, that I never lent him money for ſuch end, or at any ſuch time.</hi> I am ſorry to ſee mens writings compoſed with ſuch un-tempred morter. Let Mr. <hi>Rycraft</hi> deny if he can, that he knew he intended to go to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and that he lent him money, and deſired to be remembred to ſome in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Theſe things conſidered, ſee whether it amounts not to as much as was written of him. As for the other things he chargeth the Author of that Letter, with as the diſtemper of his head, <hi>I</hi> leave that and his owne diſtemper of head, heart and hand, to wiſe men that know them both, to judge of.</p>
            <p>And for the particular abuſes he ſaith was offered to him, and proved by oath, he had done well to have printed them, but it may be the man was aſhamed, The truth is, <hi>I</hi> have the Articles that he was accuſed of by Mr. <hi>Rycraft,</hi> One, is for kicking a ſtoole from under him, as he ſat by the fire, the other for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſting him when he was cutting his beard, to the indangering his throat, which was never proved, but denied to his face: And others are ſo frivolous, and ſo old. that they are not worth the recitall. As for his two warrants they adde juſt as much to his fidelity, as the picture before his book, to his piety.</p>
            <p>Thus may all men ſee what Mr <hi>Rycraft</hi> is, how religious, how wel-affected to the Parliament; what credit may be given to his teſtimony and to his ſtories? <hi>I</hi> ſhall only ſay thus much more of him. His malice againſt thoſe he calls In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents (if there were no more) might be a ſufficient ground to ſuſpect all the accuſations he brings againſt them: He bluſhes not to ſay he hates the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, worſe then he hates toades, and values them no more, then the dirt under his feet. Rogue and Raſcall, Brazen-face, and <hi>Billings-gate</hi> ſlut, being as good languge as he can afford them.</p>
            <p>Thus having impartially declared (being conſtrayned there to) what ſome of the witneſſes are of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſtories (not queſtioning but that others can doe as much of many others) <hi>I</hi> ſhall conſider ſome few of his expreſſions, and ſee whether theſe his witneſſes, and his expreſſions run parrallell. For he fearing his witneſſes might be ſuſpected, if not himſelfe, to have given in falſe evidence, thinks to remove all cauſe of jealouſies; and to prove the truth of all that is contained in his <hi>Gangrena,</hi> page 5. 6, by ſaying as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For divers of the errours and practices related, they are notoriouſly knowne to thouſands,</hi> I demand of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> whether thouſands, nay tens, nay any one man can witneſſe the accuſations againſt Captain <hi>Hobſon,</hi> and the truth of <hi>Joſiah Rycrafts</hi> Letter?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:113769:17"/>2. He ſaith, <hi>many errours and blaſphemies contained in his books, have been complained off, by ſufficient perſons to the Parliament, and Committees of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> I deſire him to tell me whether or no, he thinks thoſe witneſſes I have examined, ſufficient perſons to be credited, and whether he meanes not by ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient perſons, the aforeſaid Captain <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Robert Ratford,</hi> that complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Captain <hi>Hobſon,</hi> for the unjuſt things laid to his charge, or who elſe?</p>
            <p n="3">3. He affirmes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>ſome of the errours, blaſphemies are proved in the narration of the ſtories</hi> I deſire to know what ſtory hath proved the truth of thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers I have examined.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He ſaith, <hi>He himſelfe and ſome other perſons, of good note and quality, have been eye &amp; eare witneſſes of the errours, blaſphemies, &amp; practices he relates.</hi> I intreat him to declare to all the world, whether he, or any perſon of good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, was an eare witneſſe to what Captain <hi>Hobſon</hi> is charged of, and whether any of theſe good perſons ſaw the woman Mr. <hi>Rycraft</hi> tels a tale of, and if they did, let them name the perſons, and conceale them no longer.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Hee ſaith, <hi>others of theſe errours and opinions, are in divers printed books either of the Sectaries themſelves, or of perſons of note for their learning and piety.</hi> I deſire to know what bookes of the Sectaries or others upon their owne certaine knowledge, ſay that either Captain <hi>Hobſon,</hi> or his confederates, boaſted of working miracles, and caſting devills out of men poſſeſſed with them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Hee proceedeth ſaying, <hi>For any of the errours, balſphemies, put in this following Catalogue, which have come to my knowledge, by none of the former five waies above ſpecified (which yet are not many) I have had the relation of them from godly Miniſters, and underſtanding conſcientious Chriſtians, with many circumſtances of names, places, conditions, time and confident obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the certainty of them, and ſo delivered as there can be no reaſon in the world to think they ſhould be falſe, but much every way to believe them true.</hi> And he further declareth (<hi>that the reader may the more build upon the truth of all things delivered in this booke.</hi> (to his ſhame) how he went and ſent, and enquired by himſelfe and others, prompting them leſſons beforehand, that they might get w them ithout booke &amp;c. Now I deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſolution of theſe queſtions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether or no, the ſtory of Captain <hi>Hobſon,</hi> afore related; and Mr. <hi>Rycrafts</hi> ſtories came to him any of theſe waies? And if of any, then of which? If none of theſe waies, as I am confident they did not. Then ſecondly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is not guilty of apparent falſe-hood in ſaying all his relations came thus to him, when I have diſcovered two or three that did not? And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether it may not eaſily be ſuſpected Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> came as ill by many of the other ſtories, as theſe. And whether theſe may not be a preſident to judge of the reſt?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> hath not dealt very uncharitably (to ſay no worſe of it) in taking ſuch a <hi>Machivillian</hi> courſe, to ſcrew out the failings of his Brethren, and to put them to ſale.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If one ſhould take the ſame courſe as he hath done, whether he might not find farre greater, and more abominations among the Presbyterans, then is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in his <hi>Gangrena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113769:18"/>6. Thus having ſpoken to the moſt materiall ſubſtantiall things in his books and hoping I have ſufficiently cleared the guitleſſe; I ſhall a little reaſon with Mr; <hi>Edwards,</hi> and ſpeak mildly to him.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Edwards,</hi> how long will you give up your ſelfe to ſcandalize the Saints, and to fight againſt the members of Chriſt? When will you ceaſe to reprove paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with paſſion? Doe you think the Lord Chriſt takes it well at your hands, that you ſhould ſlander juſt ones, that you ſhould print the teſtimonies of vaine men againſt the Saints of the moſt high God, and ſo boldly ſtamp the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of truth, upon their forged relations? Did not you think it unjuſt, that the teſtimony of a prophane lying Apparator ſhould be received againſt you, and yet will you receive the teſtimony of as bad againſt your Brethren? When will you learne to doe as you would be done by? How long will you dote on your p ivate intereſt? Will you never ceaſe the adventuring the ruine of the whole, to ſet up your ſelfe? will nothing but <hi>Naboths</hi> Vinyard, his inheritance and life ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you? When will you ceaſe to incenſe the Magiſtrate againſt a faithfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Think not on Sacrifice, while you neglect Mercy. Good Sir. what is the reaſon you are ſo violent againſt thoſe you call Independents? are you a fraid you ſhall looſe your credit, livings, Tythes, Offerings, honour and reſpect? If theſe come falſely to you, they are better loſt then found. When will you be contented that others ſhall injoy the ſame liberty as your ſelfe? The Parliament hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Presbyterie by an Ordinance, you like it not, would you be contented to be forced to it? Doe you not expect a Toleration your ſelfe? And ſhall not your Brethen be ſuffered as well as you? When will you ceaſe to cry up the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates power in Religion, ſo long as you think they will eſtabliſh your deſires no longer? Why doe ſome of your Brethren, ſtrict Presbyterians, ſay the Parliament is a ſwarme of Sectaries, &amp; not the Parliament that was firſt choſen? Why doe any of you give out ſuch threatning ſpeaches what the Common-councell will doe before long? When will you be contented with the aſſiſtance of the truth of the moſt high to declare it ſelfe by? Is there never a wiſe man among you? never a good Souldier that can indure hardneſſe, that can fight the good fight of faith, which is only able to root out errour, even by the ſword of the Spirit. I deſire you may ſee, you are not at <hi>Dothan,</hi> but at <hi>Samariah.</hi> When wil you ceaſe <hi>Nero</hi> like to kindle a fire in the Kingdome, and ſay the Independents have done it? when will you ceaſe like <hi>Ahab,</hi> to ſay <hi>Elijah</hi> is the troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when it is your ſelfe and your Fathers houſe.</p>
            <p>All your bitter threats, accuſations, ſlanders, imprecations, nicknames, unjuſt dealing, <hi>Machivillian</hi> plotting, moves me not: I deſire your happineſſe; and that you may acknowledge your evill doing, and be aſhamed, &amp; do no more ſo wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I deſi e with all my heart, that you may ſpeedily unwrite that which you have either falſely or malitiouſly written in your bookes, and write ſo no more, then am I perſwaded your volumnes will be much leſſe, a great deale cheaper and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance better,</p>
            <p>Yo tell us your books will be believed in after ages; If you prevail according to your propheſie, it is probable. So would <hi>Oxford Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cuſſes</hi> had the Kings prevailed but they will be never the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, becauſe believed by your owne party. That you may teſtifie unto all the world your deſi es that nothing but truth may be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113769:18"/>
Bind up this with all the other anſwers to your bookes, that you intend to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord for poſterity. Triumph not becauſe al your ſtories be not ſuddenly anſwered: Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider you have agents al over the Kingdom, many may not hear of your ſtories, others may not have leaſure at preſent; others thinke it not worth the while, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded you are reſolved to have the laſt word, right or wrong, and ſo they envy you it not. What I have written, is in vindication of truth, in diſcovery of errours, of your partiallity which if you ſhall ſee, and acknowledge, that God may be gloryfied, I have gained my end.</p>
            <p>You that are the free-borne People of <hi>England,</hi> take heed whom yee believe, and what you believe, you ſee your Miniſters themſelves are ſubject to errours, liſten not to them, neither to op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe the Parliament, or thoſe that God hath made famous; in ſuffering ſo much oppoſition and contradiction for you, leſt you bring your ſelves into that lamentable ſlavery, as you had like to have done, by hearkning to the Biſhops: Sacrifice not your liberties, lively-hoods, ſervants and Brethen, which have ſacrificed their eſtates and blood for you, upon the luſt, fury, pride, avarice, or ambition of any whatſoever.</p>
            <p>You that are called to be Saints, be not diſmayed nor diſcouraged, think it not ſtrange to be reviled ſlandered and perſecuted, for this hath been the portion of the Saints in all ages: <hi>Elijah</hi> was ſlandered by <hi>Ahab,</hi> to be the troubler of <hi>Iſrael. Amos</hi> by <hi>Amaziah.</hi> The Prieſt of <hi>Bethel</hi> was accuſed for conſpiring againſt the King of <hi>Iſrael, Amos</hi> 7.10. Thus did <hi>Haman</hi> ſlander the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſaying they did not obſerve the Kings Lawes. <hi>Heſter</hi> 3.8. Thus did falſe witneſſes riſe up againſt <hi>David,</hi> laying things to his charge that he knew not of. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 27, 12. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 35.11. Thus was two men, ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> ſet before honeſt <hi>Naboth,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe he would not part with his birth-right, to beare falſe witneſſe againſt him, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying thou diddeſt blaſpheme God &amp; the King. Thus was <hi>Stephen</hi> by ſuborned men, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and accuſed falſly, &amp; ſuffered Martyrdome. Thus were the Apoſtles called ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, heretiques, deceivers, enemies to <hi>Caeſar</hi> and the like. Oh be not you troubled, for your Lord &amp; Maſter the great Lord Ieſus, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffered the contradicti n of ſinners; The <hi>Iewes</hi> accuſed him falſly, and put him to death, through the falſe ſuggeſtion, and ſlanderous accuſation of <hi>Caiaphas</hi> the high Prieſt, for blaſphemy. Follow your Maſter, <hi>bleſſe them that curſe you, doe good to them that hate you, pray for them that diſpighfully uſe you,</hi> and perſecute you; Render not Jeere for Jeere, taunt for taunt, anſwer not folly with folly, paſſion with p ſſion; But as much as in you lies, live peaceably with all men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the God of Peace ſhall be with you, and Sathan the Prince of darknes, ſhal ſhortly be trampled under your feet And the Lord Jeſus ſhall be advanced, and you though deſpiſed here, ſhall at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, apeare with him in glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
